<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cæsarion, or, Historical, political, and moral discourses in four days entertainment between two gentlemen, very pleasant and useful for all orders of men whatsoever / English'd by Jos. Walker.</title>
            <title>Cesarion ou Entretiens divers. English</title>
            <author>Saint-Réal, M. l'abbé de (César Vichard), 1639-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41078</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19611907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19611907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109194</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109194)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1694:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cæsarion, or, Historical, political, and moral discourses in four days entertainment between two gentlemen, very pleasant and useful for all orders of men whatsoever / English'd by Jos. Walker.</title>
                  <title>Cesarion ou Entretiens divers. English</title>
                  <author>Saint-Réal, M. l'abbé de (César Vichard), 1639-1692.</author>
                  <author>Walker, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 175 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Streater, and are to be sold by John Weld ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of César Vichard de Saint-Réal's Cesarion ou Entretiens divers -- NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rome --  History --  Empire, 30 B.C.-476 A.D.</term>
               <term>Rome --  Foreign relations --  Egypt.</term>
               <term>Egypt --  Foreign relations --  Rome.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109194:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CAESARION, OR <hi>Hiſtorical, Political,</hi> and <hi>Moral</hi> DISCOURSES. IN Four Days ENTERTAIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT between two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, very Pleaſant and Uſeful for all ORDERS of Men whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Engliſh'd by <hi>J. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Streater,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Weld,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:109194:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR. </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R.L.S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109194:2"/>
            <head>TO The HONOURABLE Sir <hi>Edward Windham,</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honour'd <hi>Sir,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ONe of the chiefeſt Ingredients, that ſerves to compleat a Mans happyneſs in this <hi>World,</hi> is the right adapting of things, and the fit applying them to Time, Place, and Perſons, as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. The <hi>Sun</hi> has not yet finiſh'd his Courſe through the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</note> ſince I had the Happineſs of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Obſequiouſneſs to a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Judge</hi> of your Name and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, upon another Argument: It
<pb facs="tcp:109194:3"/>hapned to be his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> he ſoon after diſappear'd, and enter'd into his Maſter's Joy.</p>
            <p>You are now, <hi>Sir,</hi> mounting the <hi>Horizon,</hi> beginning to run your <hi>Courſe,</hi> my inclination, as well as the florid Seaſon of the Year, excites me to congratulate your coming to <hi>London:</hi> Were my Abilities an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to my Mind, there ſhould not a Year nor a Day paſs, but I would expreſs my Gratitude to the Antient, Loyal, and Flouriſhing <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milys</hi> of the <hi>Wyndhams</hi> &amp; <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfords</hi> in general, <hi>(from whence you are</hi> Linealy <hi>deſcended)</hi> and to Your Self <hi>(the Top and Chief</hi> Branch) in particular, for the many Favours I ſtand obliged unto you.</p>
            <p>A Perſon of Quality, and great Merit, was pleas'd not long ago to recommend this little Book to me, as
<pb facs="tcp:109194:3"/>a thing well enough approved of by the <hi>Curious:</hi> I lookt upon it again and again, and found, that though it be little in Bulk, yet 'tis very Great in Worth and Value: What would wee have but Flowers and Marrow, Strength and Beauty; it treats of the greateſt Perſons of Antiquity, and diſcovers their ſpots and perfections; it extends to the greateſt Perſons of the times paſt and preſent: It uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally regards all Man-kind: The Famous Author of it is deſervedly reputed one of the greateſt Men of this Age. I freely confeſs, I find in it ſo many Notions applicable to myſelf, and every body elſe that has ſeen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nything of the <hi>World,</hi> and ſo many Moral as well as Political Remarks and Maxims, worthy of your Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Practice, and Obſervation, that rather than it ſhould any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:109194:4"/>lye <hi>incognito,</hi> I could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Communicating it to the <hi>World,</hi> under the auſpicious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of your <hi>Great Name;</hi> and to confirm my Hypotheſis, I find a Conformity betwixt the Interlocutor and your Circumſtances, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do make it Yours rather than any body's elſe.</p>
            <p>Proceed therefore, Noble Sir, to the <hi>Court,</hi> and to the <hi>Senat</hi>-Houſe, Imitate the worthy Example of the Famous <hi>Curtius,</hi> and prove a true Engliſh <hi>Manlius,</hi> in encouraging true <hi>Religion</hi> and Virtue, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting Juſtice Impartially, in the Sphaere God has plac'd you. I have ſeen ſeveral of your Friends treat you with their fine Coaches, Houſes, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I thought a Book, amongſt your other Recreations, might ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſerve for a Diverſion, <hi>Quel
<pb facs="tcp:109194:4"/>ch'io ho jo u'el dono.</hi> Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Almighty God to preſerve you from all temporal Dangers, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to reward you with everlaſting Happyneſs, I ever remain;</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Honour'd</hi> Sir </salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obedient Humble Servant,</hi> Joſ. Walker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:109194:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109194:5"/>
            <head>CAESARION. The <hi>firſt</hi> Day.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOthing can be truer than your Opinion, for Art and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only cannot make a Man, of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Merit, neither can Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone do it much better, and were I to chooſe, I ſhould prefer a good Education, with a moderate Talent, rather than the greateſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Parts with a Mean Education. I have particular reaſons to be of this Opinion. You know, I had the Fortune to fall into good hands in my younger Years, and though I ſignify not much, I verily believe it had been worſe with me, if I had not had that happyneſs; and I will tell you what befel me, ſince you know it already. I had indifferently well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109194:6"/>perform'd my Studys and Exerciſes at the Univerſity <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and was as well pleas'd at it my ſelf, as thoſe that had the Inſpection over me. When it was my Chance to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with ſome Gentlemen of my acquaintance, who agreed to make your Friend a Viſit in the Country, where he uſually paſſed the Summer, his Name, which was not unknown to me, gave me the Curioſity to be one of the number: I cannot tell what he diſcover'd in me that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, but when my Company were returning, he ſo courteouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd me to ſtay, that I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe him; having ſpent ſome Days in common Diſcourſe, the wearyneſs of the Country, to which young People are often ſubject, ſo prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that I began to have a deſire to ſee the Town again, however I had ſo much Complaiſance not to be gon ſo ſoon as I could have wiſh'd, but I was not diſcreet enough to conceal my uneaſyneſs, which <hi>Caeſarion</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, and ſeeking only to divert me, took occaſion to entertain me
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109194:6"/>upon the very Subject. Do not think, <hi>ſaid he one day,</hi> (having almoſt made me own it) that I blame you, it is a thing Natural to Perſons of your Age, who being like you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd with the Qualities that make them ſucceed in the World, are moſt deſirous to communicate them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to make tryal whether their Sufficiency be ſuch, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive it. I am only troubled (ſaid he) you ſhould enter into the World without knowing it, and which is worſe in beleiving it to be other than it is. I ſhall know it as others do, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> when I lanch into it: You think then, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that all thoſe, who are in it underſtand it, and how, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> could they guide themſelves in it, all their Life if they did not know it, like blind Men, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> in an irregular great Houſe, the forward Fools go by chance, and the wiſeſt grope to find the way, almoſt all the World may be conſider'd one of theſe ways, and there is nothing more difficult, than to penetrate into Men and Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are capable of Reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have a confus'd knowledg, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109194:7"/>they ſee not clearly, and deſpairing of ever ſurmounting the obſcurity, wherewith they are encompaſſ'd, they lay aſide their Circumſpection, they rather deſiſt than proceed for fear of miſſing their Aim; they Eſſay and try the beſt they can every thing they find in their way, before they truſt or rely upon it, and flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that in Time, and with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in turning round and trying e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way, at laſt they ſhall find ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and (if I may ſo ſpeak) they think they are fall'n into the lap of Fortune: You ſhall often ſee great Places occupyed by Men of this Mould, it is ſuch are cry'd up by the Vulgar ſort for Wiſe and able Men; nevertheleſs it is neither Greatneſs of Spirit, nor Nobleneſs of Mind that has plac'd them in the Station they are in, it is only becauſe they were affraid of every thing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan betimes, and from the oppoſite to what they are, from the loweſt attain to the higheſt Degree, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not to ſtay for what they knew they did not deſerve, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109194:7"/>whereunto probably they had ſome inward ſhame to aſpire; theſe kind of Men are commonly ſeen in <hi>Italy,</hi> and this kind of circumſpect cloſe Carriage, without any other Talent, has more than once mounted Perſons unto the higheſt and greateſt Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>There be others, I told you, that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves quite another way, but alſo with as little knowledg. Theſe are perſons naturally bold and reſolute, but wanting Judgment; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, indefatigable, violent in all their Motion, are always extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant in their carriage, who never al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the courſe they have taken, be it never ſo difficult, they are ſtartl'd nor reſtrain'd by nothing, and reſolve to ſurmount all Obſtacles whatſoever. This kind of Men, having no Solid Judgment, and going ſtill onwards do of courſe find many things which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impede than forward them, and ſtopping to remove that they ſhould ſhun, they many times afflict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in vain and to no purpoſe, and ſeldom find any good Succeſs, unleſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109194:8"/>it be by ſome unlook'd for Accidents, wherein Violence and Inadvertence are the chief Ingredients. It being Chance which produces theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctures they ſucceed ſometimes ſooner; whereas thoſe, who are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, never arrive thereunto un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be in a long Proceſs of Time. At firſt they be laught at, becauſe all imprudent ways are to be deſpis'd, and that nothing is more ridiculous than to ſtrive without any likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of attaining, but however they ſucceed ſoon or late. <hi>Fortune</hi> is a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhe loves to be importun'd, not to ſay forc'd, and it is almoſt the ſame of the Honours of this World as of thoſe of the next, that the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent take them by Force.</p>
            <p>I ſufficiently beleive, <hi>anſwered I,</hi> (ſeeing <hi>Caeſarion</hi> ſtop) what you have ſaid; but are there only theſe two ſorts of Men in the World, and can it be, that there are none truly wiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch Multitudes of Men? Yes doubtleſs <hi>ſaid he,</hi> there are, but many by one Accident or other are flung out of Fortuns Chariot before they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109194:8"/>come unto the end of the Race, or come out themſelves, having found by Experience that they are not fit to run the Courſe.</p>
            <p>What, <hi>anſwered I,</hi> then it ſhould ſeem by your Diſcours, that perſons of Merit are more unfit for the World than thoſe others which you have deſcrib'd, Yes, without doubt. And how can that be, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> much concern'd at his Words: Is it not much better for all to have Wiſdom than not, the danger is not in having Wiſdom, <hi>ſaid he inſtantly,</hi> nothing is more Deſirable, whatever men think, nor ſo Uſeful and Univerſal. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Fortune men attain unto who are deſtitute of it, they have only an imperfect ſenſe of their Happineſs, and always live depriv'd of the moſt ſolid ſatiſfactions, which it might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</p>
            <p>But the Evil is, that thoſe, which have too much Wiſdom, have ſome ſecret Inclinations of complying with the Maxims of the World. They doe enough to ſhew the way they ſhould go in, but they do not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109194:9"/>long in it. Can there be ſeen a greater peice of Flattery, than that of <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> kiſſing old <hi>Dennis</hi> the Tyrants feet, in asking him a Boon: It was all a wiſe Man could doe that deſir'd to live peaceably in a Tyrants Court, but he ſhould have ſtop't there, and not have anſwer'd thoſe that wonder'd at it, <hi>that</hi> Dennis <hi>had Ears in his Feet.</hi> This Action ſpake of it ſelf, and needed no Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And ſo it is, that many Men, of great parts, loſe the fruit of much paines which they take to attaine their Ends with great Men, through their weakneſs in not keeping their own Counſel.</p>
            <p>Not that this Expreſſion had any harm in it, it ſeems to me the leaſt of thoſe which we have remaining of this Excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and I much more eſteem the Anſwer of the Philoſopher <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorinus</hi> unto thoſe, who blam'd him, for ſubmitting without reaſon to the Emperour <hi>Adrian,</hi> in a Diſpute which he had with this Prince: <hi>And how could he chuſe but be in the right, that had the Command of Thirty Legions.</hi> Yet
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109194:9"/>you ſee this Expreſſion, how wiſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is, might have been taken ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill of the Emperor, if it had been appli'd unto him, or at leaſt it might have made <hi>Favorinus</hi> have forfeited the Merit of his Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>In this manner it is, that the ableſt Perſons diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they are overcome with Weakneſs and Pride, and that they cannot ſtrike Saile un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to greater Powers: The inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate freedom of <hi>Philoxenes</hi> appears much more pardonable; you know that the above mention'd <hi>Dennis</hi> having condemn'd him to the <hi>Mines</hi> for not approving ſome Verſes this Tyrant had made, being ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, <hi>Dennis,</hi> thinking he had made him more Compliable, ſhew'd him other Verſes; but <hi>Philoxenes</hi> could not prevaile with himſelf to find them any better than the former, not doubting but his Sincerity ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the like Puniſhment; inſtead of the Praiſes which the Tyrant expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he gave no other anſwer than this, <hi>to the Mines, to the Mines,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his words unto the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellites,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109194:10"/>which had lately freed him. I much better approve the equal Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this unfortunate Poet, than the Timorouſneſs of <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> and <hi>Favorinus,</hi> who having prevail'd with themſelves to doe what they ought, yet could not forbear ſaying what they ſhould not have ſpoke. I ſhould rather pardon the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate anſwer of <hi>Gondamor,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador, unto <hi>James</hi> the firſt King of <hi>England,</hi> with whom mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Court and diſcourſing in <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> the King, ſpeaking it correct and perfectly well, fell into a laughter at ſome ſlips the Count made, at which the Ambaſſador ſaid of a ſuddain, <hi>that his Latin was the Latin of a King, but the King's was that of a</hi> Pedant. It is probable, it was a ſuddain Motion which this able States-Man could not Controule, wherein I find him more excuſable than <hi>Favorinus</hi> and <hi>Ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tippus,</hi> who made the Replyes, for which I blame them, in cold Blood.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I ſuppoſe that it might be farther ſaid in the Ambaſſadours Juſtification, that how free ſoever his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109194:10"/>Anſwer was, it was of a good Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, inaſmuch as it aſcribed unto the King the glory of ſpeaking good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, wherof he was ſo Ambitious; Yes, anſwer'd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> but it was turning this Glory into ridicule, and nothing more frets great Perſons than to ſlight things, wherein they think they excel, how unbeſeeming ſoever they be unto them. And it is, whereof, the Grammarian with whom <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> diſputed about a Queſtion, was unmindful as well as you, when he anſwer'd this Prince, <hi>God forbid, Sir, that you ſhould know this matter as well as I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Anſwer, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> ſeems very polite for a Grammarian, and one could not more cleverly have inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated unto a great King, that he was in an errour. But what reſemblance is there betwixt That and our Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: The Grammarians of our times are ſeldom guilty of ſuch faults, and ſeldom diſpute with Kings. Every Age and Country <hi>have their Cuſtoms,</hi> replyd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> nevertheleſs, you ſee by theſe Inſtances, that Pride, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109194:11"/>inſeparable from thoſe that have much Wit, is but a very ill way of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Court. The greateſt Part cannot comply in ſeeing prefer'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, Perſons not worthy to be compar'd unto them, and hide ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times part of their Merit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Jealouſy in others, and by ſeeing Superiors aſſume unto themſelves the Labour and Deſert of thoſe which ſerve under them. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, to behold Favour with the ſame reſpect which is only due to Merit: But if there be any found, that have the Command over themſelves whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Sacrifice their Pride, when it doth not accord with their Intereſt, thoſe have moſt commonly ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Failing no leſs hurtful, and that is, to be ſubject to their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>This Defect, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> ſeems not unto me ſo dangerous as the other, there's Time for all things, and Men would be miſerable, if there was not a time for Recreations. Pleaſures, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd Caeſarion,</hi> are a greater hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance than you Imagine, and a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109194:11"/>Man, that enters into the World with high Deſigns, has but few how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſpare, if he intends to ſetle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in any Creditable way, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Expert betimes. Moreover, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth ſo inſenſibly ingage in troubleſome Affairs as Love, for the moſt beautiful Woemen are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the moſt reaſonable, nor the leaſt wicked, and when once they take up the trade of Gallanting, they expoſe every thing elſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the Baits, which Pride and Pleaſures lay before Perſons of Merit, and wherein moſt do ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be inſnar'd; it is, what makes them go aſtray, or at leaſt ſtops them in their courſe, whilſt others, not being detain'd by theſe things, go forwards, and fill the Places, which Perſons of Merit might juſtly have pretended unto. If it be ſo, they do ill, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> and I do not pity them in the leaſt; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs they are to be pity'd, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> and if ever you fall into any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of this Nature, you will find it is harder to reſiſt than you i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine. I mean of Perſons well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109194:12"/>as for thoſe which endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to raiſe themſelves only by the Evil which they doe, having no other means to becom Great, to ſatisfy their Revenge or their Malice, or any of thoſe Paſſions wherein their Delight does conſiſt, in vexing others, and never affording any Reſt or Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to themſelves, ſuch Perſons ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find any thing unworthy which may tend unto their Ends, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſing as may any way hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from attaining their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
            <p>I underſtand your Meaning, <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd I,</hi> at theſe words, but I cannot beleive that the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Perſons of Merit are Guilty of theſe two Faults you have mentioned; on the contrary, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> theſe defects are almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable, thoſe which are extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vain are not Amorous, or are not ſo very long. To Love, one muſt think there is want of ſomething which one has not, and not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well content with ones ſelf, ſo that Perſons, that are very Amorous, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be very Proud. Love is ſuch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109194:12"/>an overflowing Spring of groſs De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, that make but ever ſo little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection in this State, one ſhall ſcarce keep any good Opinion at all of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: So that it is very ſeldom, that any Man is affected with theſe two different Extreams at once, either of them is ſufficient to ruine him that entertains it; and it often happens, that Men paſs from one of them to the other. Being recover'd from the Love of Glory, Men fall into Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs, as <hi>Lucullus</hi> did, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo from Pleaſures Men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain thoughts of Glory, but that's but ſeldome.</p>
            <p>It is pity, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> that theſe two Paſſions, ſo incident unto Perſons of good Extraction, ſhould be ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto their Fortunes; for I ſuppoſe, that when they are ſettled in us, it is very difficult to moderate them; a thouſand times, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> more difficult than you can imagine, and it is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhew'd himſelf the Greateſt Man that ever was; <note n="*" place="margin">Pint. <hi>in his Life, &amp;</hi> Suet. c. 74, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> one of his Friends is accus'd of the moſt Criminal Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence in the World with his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109194:13"/>Wife, no leſs than Adultery and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledg both at once, and in ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick a Manner, that he is arraign'd for it before the ſevereſt Tribunal in <hi>Rome;</hi> it was a Perſon abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for his Deſigns; it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to repair this Injury, but it was no leſs convenient not to differ with him that did it, there needed an excellent temper of Mind, to find an Expedient to reconcile two ſuch oppoſite Inclinations, and any body, beſides <hi>Caeſar,</hi> would have been ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Conſideration of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour rather than Intereſt, or rather would have taken care of his Glory, which was his Intereſt to have don. He put away his Wife, ſaying, it was only becauſe ſhee was ſuſpected; and to ſhew at the ſame time ſhee was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, he refus'd to produce any E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt him, that had De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd her.</p>
            <p>If you inquire into his Pleaſures, you will therein find the ſame Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution; his Frolicks at <hi>Bithinia</hi> were only Youthful Extravagancies, which were of no great Conſequence, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109194:13"/>could only ſerve as matter of ſport unto ſome Soldiers in a day of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suet.</hi> c. 49.</note> His Gallantrys at <hi>Rome</hi> ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only to Amuſe him no longer than that they were no hindrance to his other Deſigns, but when his diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion became ſuſpected of Treaſon, and that they would Accuſe him of a Crime of State for a Paper he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in the <hi>Senat-Houſe</hi> becauſe he went about to conceale it, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plut.</hi> in <hi>Cato</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tic.</hi>
               </note> having don the part of a Gallant in conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Ladies Favours, he made no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of ſacrificing his Miſtreſſes Letter unto the ſevere <hi>Cato,</hi> who had defi'd him to do it; who no ſooner looked on it, but he ſaw it was his Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hand. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> her ſelf, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſaid of it, ſtai'd him no longer than was neceſſary to aſſure the Conqueſt of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance whereof at that time is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known; neither did ſhee hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him (as ſhee did his Leivtenant afterwards) to proſecute the Courſe of his Victories; yet, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> ſhee muſt needs be more Beautiful then; ſhee was ſo, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> for ſhee was but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109194:14"/>19 <hi>Years</hi> Old, but ſhe had not ſo much Experience as afterwards, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſhe had a particular Kindneſs for <hi>Antonius,</hi> ſhe was the Miſtreſs of his Maſter, and what Maſter?</p>
            <p>What you have ſaid of <hi>Caeſar, anſwer'd I,</hi> in that he would not proſecute his Wives Gallant, puts me in mind of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Husband that I was tould of a while ago, which was not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo Scrupulous: It was the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Dutcheſs-<hi>D'Eſtampes</hi> Husband, Miſtreſs unto <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, after the Death of this Prince, the good Man would needs begin a Law-ſute againſt his Wife, which he durſt not do any ſooner, by reaſon of the great Kindneſs the King had for the Lady as long as he liv'd; and having oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to prove this nice Point in open Court, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to be ſeen in the</hi> King<hi>'s Library.</hi>
               </note> he caus'd Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be made, wherein <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. and other cheif Lords of the Court at his requeſt teſtifi'd, in the handſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt terms they could, the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence his Wife had on the King, and the ſtrict Amity was betwixt that Prince and her. But to return
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109194:14"/>to our buſineſs, be pleas'd to let me tell you, that I don't ſee but there be as many good men as others that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to good Fortune: For if Pride and Voluptuouſneſs hinder them on one hand, their extraordinary Gifts, whereby they underſtand the World better than others, ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance them to better Succeſs: It is true, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> for ſuch as have great Endowments of Mind without any Love of Vertue, which is more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent than one imagins; for the moſt part of thoſe which are eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cunning able Oppreſſors, are only unjuſt but not wiſe, and the Vulgar only think them to be ſo, becauſe they attain their Ends, without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how or by what means they do it. But as for truly Virtuous Men how wiſe ſoever they be, they have in their Soule a Natural Incapacity of knowing the World, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them more from making any Fortune in it, than all their other Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions beſides; and the reaſon is, to remove all our Admirations, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues he without giving me leave to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109194:15"/>interrupt him; that the World being compos'd of Injuſtice, Oppreſſion, Fraud; when one is born honeſt, juſt, and ſincere; one cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive but after a long and ſad Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and when 'tis too late; <hi>I ſay,</hi> one cannot beleive, that Men can be ſo divided amongſt themſelves, and that the ſame things, which appear ſo fair or deform'd unto ſome, ſhould appear the quite contrary unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Whereas Vitious perſons, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin nothing in themſelves that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts what's practis'd in the World, have no difficulty to know what it is, and to accommodate themſelves to its Maxims. Nevertheleſs, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> if ſome ingenious Perſon, that I lookt upon as my Friend, did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it unto me Naturally and to the Life; how ſtrange ſoever it appear'd, I ſhould have no difficulty to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. For to conclude, it's no ſuch new or ſtrange thing, to hear that the World is corrupt, and that Men are unjuſt and wicked, it is what is heard dayly in every body's Mouth. It is true, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> ſmiling,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109194:15"/>it is daily ſpoken: Nevertheleſs it is only ſuch as have made long and deep Reflections in tryal of it, that can imagin unto what degree the thing is true; and you your ſelf that ſpeak, ſhould the wiſeſt Man, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, tell you exactly what 'tis, you would not beleive him. But <hi>I tell you, I would beleive him: But I tell you, you would not beleive him:</hi> You are a ſtrange Man, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> (with a kind of concernedneſs, as made him ſmile) to imagine that you know better than I, what I ſhould beleive, or what not: without doubt, I know better than you doe your own ſelf. And for what reaſon, <hi>I pray?</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that knowing the things this able Perſon would tell you, I can tell better than you, that did not know them, if you would beleive them, or if you would not beleive them: You may ſay what you liſt, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> you ſhall never make me agree unto all your Subtilties, that I ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive what was told me, when what's told me ſhould be true. And for tryal, endeavour to tell me ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109194:16"/>that you know to be moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, and you ſhall perceive by the courſe I ſhall take, whether I ſhall beleive it, or not. Some other time, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> we will make this Eſſay, if you think fit; for we have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd a good while, what diverted you at firſt may in continuance be troubleſom to you, and you may well imagin, that is not my Intention.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Day.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:109194:16"/>
            <head>CAESARION. The <hi>Second</hi> Day.</head>
            <p>NExt day I roſe much ſooner than I was accuſtom'd, the new <hi>Idea</hi>'s, which your Friends diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe wrought in me, would not let me reſt, and I was impatient to have them more fully explain'd: You muſt needs grant, that leſs matters might juſtly cauſe Admiration; no Perſon ever had a clearer apprehenſion, nor judged all things more accurately than he did, he had a peculiar way of expreſſing himſelf as ſeem'd to <hi>Charm</hi> his hearers; that's no ſtrange thing in common Converſation. Many do ſpeak very well and ſmoothly of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters daily diſcours'd of, but to expreſs ones ſelf ſo well in ſuch ſublime mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as thoſe he communicated to me,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109194:17"/>nothing ſeems more admirable in my Opinion. This incomparable and ſo rare a Gift was particularly his <hi>Talent.</hi> I have convers'd with other Perſons, that were litle inferiour to him in Parts, but you muſt as 'twere gueſs at their Meaning, and their Gifts were a Treaſure, that none but themſelves could reap any benefit by; him that moſt of all reſembled him, and that came neareſt him in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling matters, and for whom he had the greateſt kindneſs, was ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, that <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> who only under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him, was wont to ſay of him, that he ſpoke by figures darkly; and I have obſerv'd, that the greateſt and moſt profound Wits have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt difficulty, in making themſelves be underſtood.</p>
            <p>I entertain'd my ſelf with theſe thoughts, walking in a Gallery that joyned unto his Cloſet, not thinking that he was yet ſtirring, when of a ſuddain, I ſaw him coming towards me: I perceive, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that ſerious diſcourſes are ſomthing contrary to your Humour, I can only impute the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109194:17"/>cauſe of your ſo early riſing unto thoſe we had togeather <hi>Yeſterday;</hi> a little thing ſerves to ſtir up Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a perſon of your Age and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but that ſhall be avoided here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: Come let's go to Break-faſt, and let's lay aſide our Diſcourſe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals;</hi> to ſay the truth, a good nap of ſleep is better than all we can ſay; I made a ſuddain Pauſe at theſe words, looking ſteadily upon him, to look if he really beleiv'd what he ſaid, and if he judged a privation of Senſe and Motion better than the Diſcourſe we had the precedent <hi>Day:</hi> I may, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> reply in the words of one of the <hi>Antients,</hi> unto whom one ſaid, that for a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> he made but little account of <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> Why, it is even that, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> which is to be a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> but I will not uſe ſo proud an Evaſion; It is neither Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, nor Pride, which inſpire me with the thoughts, whereat you are ſo much ſurpris'd, it is a kind of Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of Soule, <hi>in fine,</hi> a kind of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Life, which would appear very reaſonable unto you, did you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109194:18"/>but know, how I have hitherto ſpent it.</p>
            <p>Our Break-faſt held not long, and the <hi>Sun</hi> was already too high to goe abroad, therefore we return'd to the Cloſet from whence he came; there were ſeveral <hi>Books</hi> lying open upon the <hi>Table,</hi> and Notes and Memorials which ſeem'd to be newly <hi>Written:</hi> I was not ſo much Maſter of my Self, but that I caſt an Eye upon them, and being about to excuſe my ſelf, he prevented me, ſaying, that they were no Secrets, and if they were, that nothing ſhould be a Secret to me in his Houſe: Then, <hi>I repli'd,</hi> that if I ſhould beleive all his Kindneſſes were real, he ſhould tell me if they were Secrets or not: Seeing you are deſirous to know the truth, they are only Abſtracts, I have drawn this morning out of the <hi>Books</hi> you ſee, for my own private Diverſion, to clear up one of the moſt curious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> wherein I reſolv'd fully to ſatisfy my ſelf; whereupon, deſiring him to impart it to me, he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109194:18"/>ſoon yeilded, and being ſat down, he began in this manner.</p>
            <p>Yeſterday we ſpake amongſt other things of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> but it may be, you don't know what kind of Man her Father was, beſides the name of <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomy,</hi> which was common unto all the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he was Surnam'd <hi>Flute-Player,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auletes. Strab.</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyr</hi> in <hi>Euſeb.</hi>
               </note> for he ſo much admir'd that Inſtrument, that he aſſembled into his Palace, thoſe which profeſs'd to be the moſt skilful at it, and vyed with them, which Play'd beſt, him or they; his Predeceſſor, named <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> being exiled from his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by his Subjects, fled unto <hi>Tyre,</hi> where he Dyed not long after, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De lege</hi> Agraria 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</note> and having no Iſſue, nor no other lawful Prince of the blood Royal to ſucceed, he made the people of <hi>Rome</hi> his Heirs, thinking he could not commit his Kingdom into ſafer hands; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the <hi>Senat,</hi> intending to reap the benefit of ſo fair a Succeſſion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd alſo Deputies unto <hi>Tyre,</hi> to recover certain ſums of Money, left there by this King at his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, but all theſe Projects fell to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109194:19"/>ground. Some <hi>Tribunes</hi> urged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Reaſons, that it was of dangerous Conſequence, that the Pleaſantneſs and Fertility of <hi>Egypt</hi> might allure too many of the People of <hi>Rome</hi> to go thither, if once they were Maſters of it; therefore the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> poſſeſſed himſelf of it, as Unkle or half-Brother to the late <hi>King,</hi> which had been formerly practis'd in that Illuſtrious <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was no Preſcription unto the Pretenſions of the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> and it was but an uncertain <hi>Title</hi> of holding a Country that had been ſo well ſetled before, unleſs ſome Means could be found to make them quit their Claim. All the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> had been Friends, or Allies unto the <hi>Romans,</hi> and upon ſeveral Occaſions, improv'd the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which accru'd thereby. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the preſent <hi>King</hi> more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly than any other: He could not be received more <hi>Authentically</hi> for a Lawful <hi>King,</hi> than by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, their Allie; and becauſe the <hi>Ceremony</hi> was uſually performed in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109194:19"/>the <hi>Capitol;</hi> the Allyance, <note place="margin">Pro Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birio Poſtumo.</note> by this means, became a Matter of Religion, than which nothing could be more <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Inviolable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the more neceſſary all this was, for him to attain to, ſo much the more difficult it was, how to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh it? The Memory of his Predeceſſors <hi>Teſtament</hi> was ſtill freſh in Mind, and as the Faults of <hi>Princes,</hi> which are not ſutable to their Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are not eaſily forgiven, although many times greater Failures are paſt by; the Sur-Name of <hi>Flute-Player,</hi> which this <hi>King</hi> had got, gained him as much Diſcredit at <hi>Rome,</hi> as it had done at <hi>Egypt:</hi> Nevertheleſs he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaired not of good Succeſs, but all the Means he uſed to attain his Ends proved fruitleſs for a long time, and in all likelihood would never have ſucceeded, had not <hi>Caeſar</hi> been <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul.</hi> This ambitious Spirit, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced every thing that favour'd his Deſigns; being cumber'd with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive <hi>Debts,</hi> finding this <hi>King</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to purchaſe by <hi>Money,</hi> what he could not attain by <hi>Right,</hi> ſold him
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109194:20"/>the Allyance of <hi>Rome,</hi> as dear as he would purchaſe it, and received for himſelf and <hi>Pompey</hi> (whoſe Intereſt was neceſſary to procure the Peoples conſent) near Six Thouſand <hi>Talents,</hi> which amounts unto Ten or Eleven Millions of our <hi>Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although this <hi>King</hi> did every year raiſe twiſe as great a Sum in his Country, he could not on a ſuddain raiſe this, without very much bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening his Subjects; they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diſſatisfi'd with him, for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the <hi>Romans</hi> to invade <hi>Cyprus,</hi> which antiently belonged unto <hi>Egypt.</hi> In this Conjuncture, the extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Impoſitions he was forced to make ſo diſpleas'd his Subjects, that they openly rebelled; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he reſolved to make his eſcape privately, to preſerve his Life. He convey'd himſelf ſo ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly away, that it was reported in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> he was ſlain, or they ſeemed to believe ſo. The Eldeſt of his three Daughters called <hi>Bernice</hi> was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>Queen</hi> in his ſtead, although he had two Sons, but much Younger
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109194:20"/>than the Daughters, and ſhee ſoon after marryed a Neighbour <hi>Prince,</hi> which pretended to be Iſſued from the Antient <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Syria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after her Father arriving at the Iſle of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> which was in his way to <hi>Rome,</hi> underſtanding that <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> (afterwards ſurnamed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tica</hi>) was alſo arriv'd there; this Prince, deſirous to entertain him of his Affaires, cauſed notice to be given him of his being there, ſuppoſing this wiſe <hi>Roman</hi> would not have fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, preſently to viſit him. But <hi>Cato</hi> ſent him word, that he ſhould come to him, if he had a mind to ſpeak with him; when <hi>Ptolomy</hi> entred his Chamber, he did not ſo much as riſe off his Seat, but ſaluting him only as an ordinary Perſon, bid him ſit down. The <hi>King,</hi> although ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd at ſuch a Reception, could not but admire, how ſo much Height and Greatneſs could meet together in the ſame Man, with ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and plainneſs, as appear'd in his Habit and Equipage: But he was much more aſtoniſh'd, when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109194:21"/>having diſcours'd of his Affairs, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> blam'd him openly, for quitting the fineſt <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the World, to goe expoſe himſelf to the Pride and Covetouſneſs of the great Men of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to ſuffer a thouſand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities by them. That it would be much his wiſeſt way, to returne aboard his <hi>Ships,</hi> and ſaile back for <hi>Egypt,</hi> to agree with his Subjects, and that he was ready to accompany him thither, if he pleas'd, and would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy himſelf in their Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> awakn'd by this Diſcourſe as from a Dreame, having ſeriouſly conſider'd his precipitate Wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Subjects in <hi>Egypt,</hi> confeſs'd his ill Conduct in forſaking his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. But his Followers, that attended him, being prevail'd with by <hi>Pompey,</hi> to have him goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the hopes, which all the World perceived after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, having diverted him from the good Counſel given him by <hi>Cato,</hi> he proceeded on his voyage, and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at leiſure for having harkned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, finding himſelf conſtrain'd
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109194:21"/>afterwards, to go from <hi>Door</hi> to <hi>Door,</hi> and from one <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to another in this proud City, ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Buſineſs like a common or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar,</hi> on whoſe help he built his greateſt Hopes was not in <hi>Rome,</hi> he was making <hi>War</hi> in <hi>Gaul.</hi> But <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey,</hi> being there, entertain'd him in his Houſe, and did him all friendly Offices. Beſides the Money I told you he received of this <hi>Prince</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jointly with <hi>Caeſar, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. Hiſt. l.</hi> 33. c. 10.</note> Ptolomy</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>Pompey</hi>'s favour by divers ſervices he had rendr'd him in his Wars againſt <hi>Mithridates,</hi> and had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray'd the Charge of 8000 Horſe in the <hi>Wars</hi> of <hi>Judea.</hi> Having therefore repreſented unto the <hi>Senate,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of his Subjects, he deſired they might be reduc'd under his Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as their Allyance obliged the <hi>Romans</hi> to do; <note place="margin">Dion. 39 <hi>ad</hi> Fam. <hi>l.</hi> 1, <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>in</hi> Piſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, <hi>pro</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birio.</note> in which affair <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi>'s Faction prevail'd, and it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd accordingly. Upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition made by the Conſul <hi>Publius Cornelius Lentulus,</hi> it was agre'd, that he ſhould draw Lots with his <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue,</hi> in what Provinces they ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109194:22"/>go to command as Proconſuls, when they had finiſh'd their <hi>Year;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Cilicia</hi> was one of thoſe nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated for them, and that it was only ſeparated from <hi>Egypt</hi> by the Coaſt of <hi>Syria,</hi> it was agre'd, that unto either of them, to whoſe Lot it ſhould fall, he ſhould be charged with the <hi>Kings</hi> Re-eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>It fell to <hi>Lentulus</hi> his Lot to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this Buſineſs, but before his Conſul-ſhip was ended, the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> hearing their <hi>King</hi> was not dead as they ſuppoſed, and that he was at <hi>Rome,</hi> diſpatched away a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>Embaſſy,</hi> to repreſent and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy their Revolt and Proceedings to the <hi>Senate;</hi> this <hi>Embaſſy</hi> was compos'd of a hundred Perſons of good Note, the cheif of which was a famous <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio <hi>de</hi> Haruſp. <hi>reſp.</hi> Strabo, <hi>&amp;</hi> Dion. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> called <hi>Dion,</hi> who had many and great Friends: <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice hereof, uſed Means, by Murder and Poiſon, to deſtroy the greateſt Part of theſe <hi>Ambaſſadours,</hi> and ſo terrified thoſe, whom he could not corrupt, nor make away, that they dared not execute their Commiſſion, nor demand Juſtice for ſo many
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109194:22"/>Murders and Violences. But the hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of his Crimes being known by every body, it was no leſs hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto him, than if they had been proſecuted in the due courſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; it in the end rendr'd the <hi>King</hi> as odious as he was deſpicable, and the vaſt Sums of Money, which he employ'd in gaining and corrupting the meaneſt and moſt covetous Perſons in the <hi>Senate,</hi> became ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly known, that it was the general and common Town-talk. There had not to that time been ſeen ſo much Corruption and Violence uſed at once about any buſineſs whatſoever; and when there was occaſion offer'd to ſpeak in publick of this Kings Affairs, his coming to <hi>Rome</hi> was always e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd one of the greateſt Miſchiefs, that ever hapn'd to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; having abſolutely complet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Debauchery and Corruption of good Manners, by his ill Practices and Example.</p>
            <p>Several other Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Allies being ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> Caelio <hi>de</hi> Haruſp. <hi>reſo</hi>
               </note> to complain of their Magiſtrates, were abuſed after the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109194:23"/>ſame manner as thoſe of <hi>Egypt</hi> were, but theſe laſt having, fill'd up the Meaſure, all honeſt Men in the <hi>Senate</hi> ſhew'd themſelves on this occaſion. <hi>Marcus Favorinus,</hi> amongſt others, a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> of the Sect of the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> was the firſt that declar'd himſelf againſt <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> he caus'd to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, that the Academiſt <hi>Dion,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Embaſſy,</hi> ſhould be ſent to the <hi>Senate</hi> Houſe to declare the Truth of things, but 'twas to little effect; the Faction of the King joyned with that of <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Lentulus,</hi> of thoſe whom he had gained with Money, and of thoſe that had ſupply'd him Money to corrupt others, acted ſo publickly in his favour, that <hi>Dion</hi> dared not appear, and <hi>Ptolomy</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to be ſlain ſoon after, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Homicide</hi> was lawfully accuſed, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</note> yet he was acquitted for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he had juſt reaſon for what he had done.</p>
            <p>Whether this <hi>Prince</hi> thought he had no more to do at <hi>Rome</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired his Preſence there; or that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generally hated, as he was, he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109194:23"/>might receive ſome Affront ſhould he ſtay there any longer, he ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter withdrew himſelf to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> into the Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> until he ſaw what Courſe his Deſtiny would take.</p>
            <p>Things were in this ſtate, towards the end of the Year, <hi>DCXCVI.</hi> of the Cities Foundation, at which time the new <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the People en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd their Office, according to Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom the 13 of <hi>December;</hi> one of which called <hi>Cajus Cato,</hi> a bold reſolute Young Man, who wanted no Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, declar'd himſelf in frequent Speeches againſt <hi>Lentulus</hi> and <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> with a general Approbation.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of the following Year, <hi>DCXCVII.</hi> an Image of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> being overthrown by <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in Mount <hi>Alban,</hi> according to the ancient Cuſtom, the <hi>Books</hi> of the <hi>Sybils</hi> were conſulted to know what this Prodigy portended, and in them theſe Words were found. <hi>If a</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Egypt <hi>has need of help, and addreſſes himſelf unto you, do not refuſe him your Friendſhip, nevertheleſs grant him not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109194:24"/>Succours, for by ſo doing you will ſuffer much Damage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſual Manner was, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate theſe kind of <hi>Oracles,</hi> firſt to the <hi>Senate,</hi> to examine if it were lawful to divulge them. But <hi>Cajus Cato,</hi> fearing the <hi>Kings</hi> Faction might reſolve to ſuppreſs this, it being ſo much to this <hi>Prince</hi>'s prejudice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out farther Ceremony, preſented the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> which kept theſe ſacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords unto the People, and by Virtue of the Power his <hi>Tribune-ſhip</hi> gave him, obliged them to expoſe unto the Publick, what they had therein found without conſulting the <hi>Senate</hi> in the matter.</p>
            <p>This unexpected proceeding was as 'twere another <hi>Thunder-clap</hi> to <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and <hi>Lentulus.</hi> The words of the <hi>Sybil</hi> were too preciſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly calculated to the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, not to imprint in the People the Impreſſions, the <hi>Kings</hi> Enemies deſired, and <hi>Lentulus,</hi> whoſe <hi>Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> was expired, not willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in Perſon the diſgrace of revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109194:24"/>the <hi>Senat</hi>'s Decree, which had appointed him to reſtore <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> went away immediatly into his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. In fine, a few days after, one of the new <hi>Conſuls,</hi> called <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> an open Enemy unto <hi>Pompey,</hi> having repreſented the Senſe of the <hi>Oracle</hi> to the <hi>Senate;</hi> it was reſolved, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſhould be given unto it, and that it was not ſafe for the Common-Wealth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad</hi> Fam. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>ad</hi> Q. F. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. Ap. <hi>in</hi> Sir. <hi>&amp;</hi> Parth. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> to re-eſtabliſh the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> by force of Armes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſarion</hi> ſtopping at theſe words, as 'twere to recollect what he had elſe to ſay; I could not hide my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration from him, that in ſo learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Age, the moſt Illuſtrious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly in the World, ſhould give credit to ſo unlikely a Superſtition. You muſt not wonder at it, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> unto me: A whole Aſſembly may have ſome difference upon a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſcore, which it may be not one of thoſe Perſons would doe whereof it's compos'd, were they alone, and Men are very different when they are together,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad</hi> Fam. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1.</note> of what they be when they are ſingle and apart. No body
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109194:25"/>doubts, but this ſuppos'd Oracle was contriv'd on purpoſe in hatred of <hi>Pompey,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad</hi> Fam. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1.</note> who eſpous'd the <hi>Kings</hi> Intereſts, and whoſe ambitious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were alike ſuſpected and known. Beſides, it is moſt certain that the generality of good Men, at that time made no eſteem of the <hi>Books</hi> of the <hi>Sybils.</hi> They were much admir'd indeed at the firſt beginning of the Common-Wealth, when the <hi>Roman</hi> Ignorance was as great as their Vertue; but ſince Learning had paſſed out of <hi>Greece</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> thoſe kind of <hi>Propheſies</hi> were not regarded, and the three <hi>Books</hi> ſold by the <hi>Sybil</hi> of <hi>Cuma</hi> at ſo great a price unto the firſt of the <hi>Tarquin's,</hi> having been burnt in the <hi>Capitol</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Sylla,</hi> it not being permitted to have Copies of them, other nice kind of <hi>Books,</hi> that had been gather'd throughout the Empire, to ſupply their place when the <hi>Capitol</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built, not being of the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, little heed was given to them; but let us re-aſſume the Courſe of our Hiſtory.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:109194:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ptolomy</hi> having obſerv'd during his ſtay at <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence betwixt him and <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> tended but little to his advantage, becauſe this <hi>Proconſul</hi> had many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes; at his departure from thence he left one <hi>Ammonius,</hi> an <hi>Egyptian,</hi> his <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> there in his ſtead, and charged him not to inſiſt upon the order of <hi>Senat,</hi> that had appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Lentulus</hi> to act in his Re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; moreover judging it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, this Commiſſion ſhould be put in the hands of ſome Perſon of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and extraordinary Intereſt and Reputation, ſeeing it could not be executed by Force, by reaſon of the <hi>Oracles</hi> Prohibition; he Order'd his <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> to demand, it ſhould be committed into the hands of <hi>Pompey,</hi> attended only with two Bayliffs.</p>
            <p>Two Bayliffs, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> to reduce a whole Kingdom to Obedience; <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd Caeſarion,</hi> the Majeſty and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect at that time born unto the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Name throughout the World, may be demonſtrated from as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable things as that; did you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109194:26"/>hear, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> of that great <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour</hi> ſent by the <hi>Senate,</hi> the Age before that we ſpeak of, unto <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus</hi> the famous King of <hi>Syria?</hi> This Prince, having almoſt ſubdued the whole Kingdom of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was going to beſeige <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in which place the <hi>Royal Family</hi> had taken Sanctuary, being deſtitute of any other help, but the protection of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cajus Popilius</hi> was the Name of this Ambaſſadour, who meeting this proud <hi>King,</hi> being an Ally of <hi>Rome,</hi> four miles from this flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City, having ſaluted him, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him his Hand in token of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; <hi>Popilius</hi> made no other anſwer to his Civility, but preſenting him the <hi>Senates</hi> Letters bid him read them. <hi>Antiochus,</hi> having read them, ſaid, he would adviſe with his Friends in the Caſe; but <hi>Popilius</hi> drawing a Circle about the <hi>King</hi> with a Rod he had in his Hand; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>you paſs the Limits of this Circle, give the</hi> Senate <hi>your Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:109194:26"/>
            <p>The <hi>King,</hi> being ſurpris'd with ſo reſolute a demand, pauſed a little, and then promis'd to do what the <hi>Senate</hi> commanded; whereupon <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius</hi> ſtretched out his hand, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the <hi>King,</hi> a Friend and Ally of <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Antiochus,</hi> quitting all he had conquer'd, ſoon after depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>Egypt</hi> by the time prefixt.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, ſaid I, the two Bayliffs are not ſo ſtrange as this Adventure, and it had been neceſſary in this jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, that this <hi>King</hi> had reſembled one of our <hi>Kings,</hi> that boaſted his Horſe carry'd all his Council, but if you pleaſe, let us return unto <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hopes, replied <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> which <hi>Ptolomy</hi> had in him, was the more juſt, becauſe this Illuſtrious <hi>Roman</hi> was at that time in the higheſt pitch of his Glory, by reaſon of the good ſucceſs in conquering <hi>Mithridates,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rex poſt.</hi> Alex. Max. Cic. Luc.</note> the greateſt King that <hi>Aſia</hi> enjoy'd, ever ſince the days of <hi>Alexander.</hi> Two Tribunes of the People, one called <hi>Lupus,</hi> the other <hi>Caninius,</hi> being both devoted unto <hi>Pompey,</hi> having in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109194:27"/>read Letters from <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> whereby this Prince deſired of the Senate, <note place="margin">Plut. <hi>in</hi> Pompe.</note> that <hi>Pompey</hi> might be entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the power of reſtoring him to his Kingdom; thereupon grew up amongſt the Senators ſundry dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publius Servilius Iſauricus</hi> was of opinion not to give him any Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance at all, and it had been ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by Plurality of Voices, had not <hi>Caninius</hi> oppoſed himſelf thereto, as his Office of Tribune qualified him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hortenſius, Marcus Lucullus,</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> maintain'd, that the former Decree of the Senate ought to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in behalf of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and that ſeeing the Oracle permitted him not to re-eſtabliſh the <hi>King</hi> by force of Arms, it behoved him to find out ſome other convenient way of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him. <hi>Craſſus</hi> was of opinion, that Commiſſion ſhould be given to three Ambaſſadors, which ſhould be indifferently choſe out of the Senate. <hi>Bibulus,</hi> a declar'd Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and by conſequence of <hi>Pompey</hi> his Son in Law, concurr'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109194:27"/>alſo in the ſame Opinion, of ſending three Ambaſſadors with <hi>Craſſus,</hi> but excepting all ſuch of the <hi>Senate,</hi> which bore any other Office, as <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> and <hi>Lentulus</hi> did. This Opinion was liked by the new Conſuls <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> and generally by all thoſe that had been Conſuls, except <hi>Volcatius</hi> an intimate friend of <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi>'s and <hi>Afranius,</hi> who had been his Lieutenant againſt <hi>Sertorius,</hi> and againſt <hi>Mithridates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time, his Geatneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſuſpected unto moſt of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> eſpecially by reaſon of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance and Intimacy with <hi>Caeſar.</hi> It was obſerv'd a good while, that he always ambition'd the greateſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and that, as ſoon as ever one Office was expir'd, he preſently graſped after ſome other, at any rate; ſo that having put an end to the Civil Wars in <hi>Italy,</hi> which took beginning preſently after the death of <hi>Sylla,</hi> he procured to be ſent into <hi>Spain</hi> againſt <hi>Sertorius,</hi> then ſoon after againſt the <hi>Pirates;</hi> afterwards by his Factions, he cauſed <hi>Lucius Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:109194:28"/>to be recall'd in the midſt of his ſucceſſes againſt <hi>Mithridates,</hi> and to be ſent himſelf in his ſtead, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>Legions</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt:</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, after the Death of this Prince, there being no conſiderable Wars ſtirring, he obtein'd a new Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to provide <hi>Corn</hi> for the ſpeedy releif of the neceſſities, that <hi>Italy</hi> was then reduc'd unto. The <hi>Romans</hi> thought it no leſs glorious, to ſupply the wants of their Country, than it was to expel their Enemies; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this latter Commiſſion ſtirr'd up all the Envy imaginable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, even thoſe that ſeem'd to be his Friends before, upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, refuſed to favour his Deſigne, in re-eſtabliſhing the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plut. in</hi> Pom.</note> becauſe he had the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of providing <hi>Corn</hi> for five <hi>Years,</hi> whereas it was againſt the Laws, that any ſhould Execute two Offices at once.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad</hi> Fam. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Lucius Libo,</hi> whoſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter afterwards Marryed <hi>Pompey's</hi> youngeſt Son, a <hi>Tribune</hi> named
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109194:28"/>
               <hi>Plautius Hipſaeus,</hi> who had been his Quaeſtor againſt <hi>Mithridates,</hi> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all his Friends ſo highly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for him in this Matter, that no body made any doubt, but that he earneſtly deſired this Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, although he declared it not openly himſelf.</p>
            <p>He had receiv'd too many and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick favours from <hi>Lentulus,</hi> to have dar'd to oppoſe him openly. It was <hi>Lentulus,</hi> that procur'd for him the Power of the <hi>Corn</hi> buſineſs, but this important Service, which had incurr'd to this <hi>Pro-conſul</hi> the hatred of all thoſe which pretended to this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, did never a whit the more aſſure him of the Friendſhip of <hi>Pompey,</hi> for no thing indeed could aſſure it. <hi>Cicero</hi> who knew him better than any Man, and who had the greateſt Obligation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame <hi>Proconſul,</hi> for his being releas'd from Baniſhment, ceaſed not to importune <hi>Pompey,</hi> in favour of their common Benefactor; and as this Oraror in this Rancoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, perform'd the part of a grateful friend; <hi>Pompey</hi> on his part, thought beſt to diſſemble his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109194:29"/>Ingratitude, ſo far as to make a Speech in the <hi>Senat</hi>-Houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pompeius</hi> fremit queri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed utrum fronte an men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 14. Ad Att.</note> with all the Vigour and ſeeming Kindneſs could be, in behalf of <hi>Lentulus:</hi> But there was very little credit given to it, he was obſerv'd to compaſs his Ends by ſuch oblique Courſes, that there was no truſt given * to any thing he either did, or ſaid.</p>
            <p>You give there, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> interrupting him at theſe words, a ſtrange Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the great <hi>Pompey,</hi> and I could never have thought it, by his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name and great Reputation. You meane, anſwer'd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> the <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalia;</hi> but you ſhall find afterwards, that <hi>Lucan</hi> has repreſented him quite different from what he was, and that many times there is no good ground for the greateſt Reputations. I confeſs, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> at my turn, if things were as you ſay, <hi>Lentulus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be pity'd; for there can nothing be more cruel, than to be abus'd by a Perſon, that one has ſerv'd, and to be expos'd to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Enemies, that one has got by ſerving his Friend. But I expected
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109194:29"/>however, that <hi>Pompey's</hi> Enemies would forbeare perſecuting <hi>Lentulus,</hi> when they ſaw he was betray'd by him: You are much deceiv'd, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> this Treaſon repair'd not the micheif don them by <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi> in preferring <hi>Pompey</hi> before them, and their hatred was no way mitigated, on the contrary they us'd all means poſſible in protracting the buſineſs, becauſe it could not be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, but in favour of the <hi>Pro-Conſul;</hi> for not agreeing to employ <hi>Pompey</hi> in the buſineſs, nor any one elſe to his prejudice, ſhould a final reſolution be taken, they could not avoid confirming the former Act of the <hi>Senat,</hi> which had nominated <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi> on the termes the Oracle had preſcrib'd, of ſetling the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> otherwiſe, than by force of Armes.</p>
            <p>In effect, the Opinion of <hi>Bibulus</hi> of granting a Commiſſion about the the matter in agitation to three Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, excluding amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Lentulus,</hi> out of the number, becauſe they were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109194:30"/>of other Offices, was not inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon next day, as it had been till then, and there was only deliberated about thoſe which confirm'd <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and thoſe which propos'd <hi>Pompey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſual form was that they ſhould firſt confider that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd <hi>Lentulus,</hi> becauſe it had been propos'd by Conſulary Perſons; whereas the other had only been propos'd by the <hi>Tribunes:</hi> But <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> one of thoſe <hi>Tribunes,</hi> ſeeing which way the <hi>Senat</hi> was inclin'd, fear'd, that if they ſhould begin to deliberate upon <hi>Lentulus,</hi> that he he would be confirm'd in ſpight of his Enemies; to prevent this Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and to uſe his laſt endeavour in in his friends behalf, it came into his minde to propoſe, that it was moſt expedient, to deliberate of <hi>Pompey</hi> firſt.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the <hi>Senatours</hi> highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected this Innovation, but the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls</hi> did not ſo, they were ever of the Judgment of <hi>Bibulus,</hi> equally contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both unto <hi>Lentulus</hi> and <hi>Pompey.</hi> But ſeeing the cauſe almoſt deſerted,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109194:30"/>they ſided with thoſe that favour'd <hi>Pompey,</hi> not with intent to confirm him, but with a Deſign, to hinder <hi>Lentulus</hi>'s friends from confirming him, in ſpending all the Seſſion as the former had been, in frivolous Diſputes. To this purpoſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, not as the others did, againſt the <hi>Tribunes</hi> unaccuſtom'd proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither did they much regard it; and keeping up the Feud amongſt the ſeveral Factions, by this dubious proceedings inſtead of compoſing differences, which they might eaſily have don by their Authority, they did what they deſir'd, which was, that nothing at all ſhould be don, and ſo they parted the third time, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out coming to any Concluſion.</p>
            <p>The Enemies of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> for to fruſtrate his Pretenſions, only need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſtave it off to the Sitting fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which was to be the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad.</hi> Fam. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 4.</note> 15 of <hi>January,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Senate</hi> could not meet all the reſt of the Month, for ſundry reaſons, that time being appointed for giving Audience to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors,</hi> ſo that no other buſineſs was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109194:31"/>to be heard, until they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd. The laſt day therefore of this Seſſion, <hi>Curion</hi> the Father, who had not hitherto appear'd in the Matter, ſpake ſmartly, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pompey,</hi> and againſt <hi>Lentulus.</hi> And although <hi>Bibulus</hi> had almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd the Opinion, which he at firſt gave, of joyning with the friends of <hi>Lentulüs</hi> againſt <hi>Pompey, Pompey</hi>'s party grew ſo inſolent, and took ſuch Liberty in ſpeaking, that every one ſpake and concluded what they liſted; ſo that this Sitting alſo was as fruitleſly ſpent, as the others had been before.</p>
            <p>Yet although the pretenſions of <hi>Lentulus</hi> were ſtill delay'd by theſe Artifices; the <hi>Tribune Cato,</hi> fearing yet that it might ſucceed, propos'd to the People about the beginning of <hi>February,</hi> to diſcharge him of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Cilicia.</hi> His Son, as the manner was in the like caſes, went into mourning to ſolicit for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his friends uſed all manner of Endeavours in his behalf. It was ſtrictly prohibited, to treat with the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109194:31"/>People about any buſineſs whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, on the Days wherein the flight of Birds was obſerved; and all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats having the priviledg to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them when they pleas'd, <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>'s friends made uſe of this Artifice, to hinder the People from deliberat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Cato</hi>'s Propoſition againſt him. A little while after, another <hi>Tribune,</hi> called <hi>Lucius Racilius,</hi> who was his Friend, removed this obſtacle by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing his Authority, after the uſual form, according to the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of his Office. For when a <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune</hi> oppos'd himſelf unto what the reſt had propos'd, they could not proceed any farther without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the People, which was difficult and rare to be ſeen.</p>
            <p>During theſe Tranſactions, <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> making a Speech to the People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout another buſineſs, inſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving thanks and commendations, he was ſcoff'd and revil'd; amongſt other things he was tax'd, for ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the People for want of Corn, their indignation proceeded ſo farr, that they accus'd him of the moſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109194:32"/>horrible Crimes, but eſpecially, they jeer'd him publickly, at his deſign of reſtoring the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Tribune Cato</hi> ſome time after, in the <hi>Senat,</hi> preſſed him ſo hard, and was ſo favourably heard by the whole Aſſembly, that <hi>Pompey,</hi> how cloſe ſoever he carri'd it, could not at leaſt conceale his trouble and grief. Theſe two misfortunes, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plainly diſcover'd unto him, the Envy which all the World bore him, made him wholly lay aſide all farther thoughts of the buſineſs of <hi>Egypt:</hi> And ſome time after, <hi>Lentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> writing to him in ſuch a way, as if he believ'd, he never had thoughts of ſeeking after it; he was ſo pleas'd with the <hi>Letter,</hi> that he forthwith imbrac'd <hi>Cicero</hi>'s opinion of the thing, in wiſhing it to their Common friend.</p>
            <p>I perceive then, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> it was not <hi>Pompey</hi> alone, that knew how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble in thoſe dayes, and <hi>Lentulus</hi> knew how to doe it as well as him. It is not a thing to be blam'd, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> to wink at the failing of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109194:32"/>our friends, when this Connivance may recal them to their Duty; on the contrary ther's nothing more manly and generous, and that was the caſe, as you ſee, of <hi>Lentulus.</hi> But to diſſemble as <hi>Pompey</hi> did, by his evil deſigns againſt his friend, and to leave no meanes unattempted to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect them, is the baſeſt of all treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>But what expectation, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> could <hi>Cicero</hi> have for <hi>Lentulus,</hi> and what could this <hi>Proconſul</hi> do, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out imploying open Force againſt a great Kingdom, where the fame of the Oracle had been ſpread, which enjoyn'd, that it ſhould not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqu'd by open Force: You are not very deep ſighted, <hi>anſwer'd Caeſarion.</hi> The Oracle only prohibited furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>King</hi> with an Army to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh him: Could not <hi>Lentulus</hi> have left the <hi>King,</hi> as 'twere <hi>incognito,</hi> in ſome place near the Borders, and in the mean time with a good Army, goe beſeige <hi>Alexandria?</hi> then when he had taken it, leaving good Garriſons behind him, come back and ſend the <hi>King</hi> into his Kingdom, who ſhould
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109194:33"/>find all places ready to receive him? and were not this, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> to re-eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh him by force of Armes, againſt the Prohibition made by the <hi>Sybil;</hi> not at all, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> for in the time <hi>Lentulus</hi> ſubdu'd the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> was not with him; and when the <hi>King</hi> was return'd, there was no Army, and ſo it could not be ſaid that he had an Army given him, to reſtore him to his Country. You jeere, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> to reaſon after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if it were not all one, that <hi>Ptolomy</hi> had been with <hi>Lentulus,</hi> or had not been with him, ſeeing the <hi>Proconſul</hi> ſubdu'd <hi>Egypt</hi> by force. You are dul of Apprehenſion, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> but if you will not believe me, it may be you will give more credit to <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Cicero.</hi> Harken then to the very words of this Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, writing to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> as well in his own Name, as in <hi>Pompey's:</hi>
               <q>It is for you to judge what you can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, being Maſter of <hi>Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and if you conceive it feaſible, to take <hi>Alexandria</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Egypt,</hi> doubtleſs it is for your Credit and for the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109194:33"/>that you ſhould haſten thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with your Fleet and Army, leaving the <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Ptolomais,</hi> or ſome other adjacent place, to the end, that when you have appeas'd the Rebellion, and plac'd good Garriſons every where, the <hi>King</hi> might returne thither. In this manner you will re-eſtabliſh him, as the <hi>Senat</hi> at firſt appointed you, and he will be reſtor'd without Force, as our <hi>Zealots</hi> affirm, the <hi>Sybil</hi> appointed it ſhould be done.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sic have to, me, cum illo re ſaepe commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicata, de illius ad te ſententia, &amp; auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ſcribere; Te poſſe perſcribere, qui Ciliciam Cyprumque tenes, quid office<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; quid conſequi poſſis, &amp; ſi res fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatem habitura videatur, ut Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driam atque Aegyptum tenere poſſis, eſſe &amp; tui, &amp; noſtri Imperii dignitatis, Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaide, aut aliquo propinquo loco, Rege collocato, te cum claſſe atque exercitu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiſci Alexandriam, ut cum illam pace praeſidiisque firmaris, Ptolomaeus redeat in regnum. Ita fore ut per te reſtituatur, quemadmodum initio Senatus cenſuit, &amp; ſine multitudine reducatur, quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum homines religioſi Sibyllae placere dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt.</hi> Ad Famil, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 7.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:109194:34"/>
            <p>You ſee by this, <hi>continued Caeſarion,</hi> making a little pauſe, the truth of what I told you at firſt, that in the main, the <hi>Sybil</hi>'s Books were not much valu'd: For <hi>Cicero</hi> adds in plain Terms, that how ſtrange ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the advice, he gives to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> does appear, <hi>all the World ſhould judge of it by the Succeſs; ſo that he ſhould on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be careful to take his meaſures ſo well as to be ſure not to fail in his Deſign; and if he did not, he had as good do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I freely confeſs, that I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have thought of ſuch a cunning peice of Policy, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> being able not to contain any longer, and I ſee thereby, <hi>Heaven may be compounded with at any time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But pray, let me know if this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſucceeded. <hi>Lentulus,</hi> reply'd <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarion,</hi> did not think himſelf ſtrong enough to follow this Counſel, and the Troops, which he could private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have furniſhed <hi>Ptolomy</hi> withal, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared not ſufficient unto this <hi>Prince,</hi> to reſtore him without the Preſence of the <hi>Pro-Conſul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:109194:34"/>
            <p>But there was another which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded at the ſame time in <hi>Syria,</hi> who was not altogether ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. It was <hi>Aulus Gabinius,</hi> one tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour'd by <hi>Catiline,</hi> of whom he had been tenderly belov'd in his Youth, and his Actions did not derogate from his Education. He was eſteem'd a great Dancer, <note place="margin">Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 39. Strab. <hi>l.</hi> P7. <hi>ad</hi> Catili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matorem ſuum Ejus vir</hi> Catili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, <hi>l.</hi> 3. c. 14.</note> as <hi>Ptolomy</hi> was a <hi>Player</hi> upon the <hi>Flute;</hi> he rifled his own Province worſe than the <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditty</hi> or wild <hi>Arabians</hi> would have done, had they had their Will. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially he exerciſed his Cruelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſorts of <hi>Publicans,</hi> out of Envy againſt the Order of Knights they were of, who had in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent manner defended <hi>Cicero</hi> againſt him; for it was under his <hi>Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and eſpecially by his Authority that this Orator was condemn'd to to Baniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ex eventu homines de tuo conſilio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimaturos; ſi exploratum tibi ſit, non cunctandum; ſin dubium, non conan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> ibid.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:109194:35"/>
            <p>His proceedings had rendr'd him ſo odious at <hi>Rome,</hi> that having accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Cuſtom given the <hi>Senat</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a War, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſular in Piſonem ad.</hi> Q.F. <hi>l,</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 7.</note> that he had began and brought to a happy Concluſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were ſlighted, and little or no notice taken of them, which had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been done before unto any elſe beſides, neither would the <hi>Senate</hi> vouchſafe to thank the Gods in his Name. But he grew never the wiſer nor better for this diſgrace. There being no more to be got in <hi>Syria,</hi> which he had utterly ruin'd by his Oppreſſions, he deſign'd a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Arabians,</hi> when <hi>Mithrida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Prince of the <hi>Parthians</hi> came to crave his aſſiſtance, who was expell'd by the <hi>King</hi> his Brother out of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> which had been aſſigned unto him for his Portion. Although it was ſtrictly prohibited by Law, that no <hi>Pro-conſul</hi> ſhould go out of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, nor undertake, or declare any War whatſoever, without the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi>'s expreſs Order, yet <hi>Gabinius</hi> made no Scruple of ingaging in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109194:35"/>this Quarrel, in hope of making ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the great Riches of theſe two <hi>Princes,</hi> by their mutual animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. He had already paſſed <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> with his Army, to this purpoſe, when <hi>Ptolomy</hi> met him with Letters from <hi>Pompey,</hi> the Friend and Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of them both, who was then new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared <hi>Conſul</hi> for the enſuing Year, by which Letters, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd <hi>Gabinius</hi> to hearken to the Propoſals this <hi>Prince</hi> ſhould make him, concerning his re-eſtabliſhment in his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Whether it was out of regard to the <hi>Sybils</hi> Oracle, or that the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> War ſeem'd leſs difficult and more profitable, than that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> moſt of the cheifeſt Men about <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binius</hi> declared themſelves againſt <hi>Ptolomy, Antonius</hi> only excepted, who though very Young, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap. l.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> Plut. <hi>in</hi> Ant.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Cavalry,</hi> and was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one of the <hi>Triumvirs,</hi> and an intimate friend of this <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the more the buſineſs was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik'd, the more <hi>Gabinius</hi> reſolv'd to be courted, and to make his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109194:36"/>by it. <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> who reſolv'd to ſpare no coſt, to procure his conſent, offer'd for the General and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Ten Thouſand <hi>Talents,</hi> which amounts, in our <hi>Money,</hi> to about Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen <hi>Millions,</hi> the greateſt part to be paid in advance, and the reſt as ſoon as he was reſtor'd. It was no hard matter for <hi>Antonius,</hi> to prevaile with <hi>Gabinius</hi> to accept this offer, who thirſted more after it than he himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Egypt</hi> was govern'd by the <hi>King</hi>'s Eldeſt Daughter, who I told you was Proclaim'd <hi>Queen,</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> ſled away. The <hi>Syrian Prince</hi> that Marryed her, prov'd a very mean and brutiſh Perſon. Whether it was his Natural Love to Riches, or that he thought not himſelf well Eſtabliſh'd, he reſolved to make uſe of his Time. His firſt care was, to take the Body of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, out of the Coffin of Maſſy <hi>Gold,</hi> which he converted to his own uſe, having, till then lain quietly therein, and caus'd it to be put into one of Glaſs. But this, and ſeveral other the like
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109194:36"/>Actions by him done, render'd him equally odious unto the <hi>Queen</hi> and her Subjects, ſo that ſhe caus'd him to be ſtrangl'd not long after. And the friends of this <hi>Princeſs,</hi> ſeeing the need ſhee had of the Support and Counſel of ſome Perſon of eminent Fortune and Merit, againſt her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſigns, they made choiſe of one of the <hi>Princes</hi> of the greateſt Fame in all the Eaſt, for her ſecond Husband.</p>
            <p>He was nam'd <hi>Archelaus,</hi> Son of the great <hi>Mithridates,</hi> though he was not really, but the Son of his Leivtenant. This Leivtenant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpected by his <hi>Prince,</hi> about his managment of a Treaty with <hi>Sylla,</hi> thought it his wiſeſt way, in time to change his Party to preſerve his life, and joyning himſelf to the <hi>Romans,</hi> he much enrich'd himſelf thereby; and alſo receiv'd the titles of Friend and Allye of <hi>Rome.</hi> His Son, following his Example, ingag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo in the ſame party, and was made <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Comagene</hi> by <hi>Pompey,</hi> in recompence of Service, perform'd
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109194:37"/>by him. Having contracted an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Friendſhip with <hi>Gabinius,</hi> in a time when this <hi>Proconſul</hi> made War in thoſe Provinces, under other Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, as ſoon as he came to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in cheif in <hi>Syria,;</hi> this <hi>Prince</hi> went to him, with a deſigne of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending him in the <hi>Parthian</hi> War, there to Merit, by his Service, new Favours and Commands under the <hi>Romans.</hi> But the <hi>Senate</hi> not approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this deſigne, and the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſoliciting him at the ſame time, he withdrew himſelf privatly from <hi>Gabinius</hi> to conſummate his Marriage, <note place="margin">Strab. <hi>l.</hi> 17.</note> judging the <hi>Romans</hi> would hinder it, ſhould they have knowledg of it.</p>
            <p>About ſix Months after this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and in the Spring of the yeare D CX CV III under the <hi>Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Craſſus, Gabinius</hi> left his Province to the care of his Son, <note place="margin">Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 39. T. <hi>liv.</hi> 105. Egeſip. <hi>l.</hi> 1. c. 21. Joſe. Plut. <hi>in</hi> Anto.</note> who was but young and weakly guarded; and with his Army marched through <hi>Paleſtine</hi> towards <hi>Egypt.</hi> He received all the aſſiſtance could be deſired, from <hi>Antipater</hi> the Father of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great, into
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109194:37"/>whoſe hands he committed the chief Power of thoſe Countries after the Wars, I told you he had in thoſe parts. The greateſt difficulty at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent was, what courſe was beſt to take from thence to the fronteers of <hi>Egypt,</hi> over great and deep ſands, full of Serpents, or by the Fens and Marſhes of the Lake <hi>Sirbonides,</hi> in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which there was no freſh water to be had: But <hi>Antonius</hi> marching before with the <hi>Cavalry,</hi> had ſo well prepar'd the way for the reſt of the Army, that it all arriv'd ſafely at <hi>Peluſium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a large, ſtrong and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Sea-port Towne, which was, as may be ſaid, the Key of the whole Kingdom, and the only convenient Haven neere the Sea: But it being cheifly inhabited and defended by <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe neighbourhood, togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the conveniency of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, invited them thither; it was no difficult matter for <hi>Antipater,</hi> by the familiarity and commerce he had with them, to perſwade them, to deliver the City to the <hi>Romans:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109194:38"/>Ptolomy</hi> being tranſported with Joy at ſo happy a beginning, alſo with rage againſt the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> would have put all that were in the City to the Sword, but that <hi>Antonius</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him from it: The Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divided into two Battalions, ſoon after marched forwards, and meeting that of <hi>Egypt</hi> commanded by <hi>Archelaus,</hi> fought and took <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelaus</hi> priſoner, and defeated his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Gabinius</hi> might ſoon have put an end to this War, in carefully keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Prince,</hi> in whome the <hi>Queen</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> put their whole confidence. But he thought, that if he ſhould ſo ſoon ſettle <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and with ſo little labour, this <hi>Prince</hi> would uſe ſome pretext of breaking his word, and not pay the Mony according to his promiſe: He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought it better, to get as great a Ranſom as he could by his Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and to give him opportunitys of making his eſcape, in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their former friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Afterwards he caus'd his Fleet to ſaile up the River, where they met
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109194:38"/>the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Fleet, which was alſo worſted, and then he march'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> with his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces. <hi>Archelaus,</hi> being retir'd thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, march'd forth with his Army to give him Battel. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Valer,</hi> Max. <hi>l.</hi> 8. c. 1.</note> When he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped and would intrench him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the <hi>Egyptians</hi> cry'd out, that he ſhould get Mercenaries to work at the publick charge, if he would; you may eaſily gueſs what reſiſtance ſuch Soldiers would make. <hi>Archelaus,</hi> who in all likelihood acquitted himſelf better than his Soldiers, <note place="margin">Dio. <hi>l.</hi> 1. P. 58. Caeſar. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>of Sivil War.</hi> T. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. 150. Strab. <hi>l.</hi> 12, 17, <hi>in</hi> Piſon. Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 39. <hi>ad.</hi> Att. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 9. Por. <hi>in</hi> Eaſub. Ege. <hi>l.</hi> 1. c. 2.</note> caus'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf [ſeeing all was loſt) to be kill'd: <hi>Antonius</hi> having contracted friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with this Unfortunate <hi>Prince,</hi> whilſt he was with <hi>Gabinius,</hi> caus'd his Body to be found out amongſt the Slain, and to be Royally In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gabinius</hi> plac'd very ſtrong Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons of <hi>Gauls</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exandria,</hi> under <hi>Roman</hi> Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Ptolomy</hi> being thus reſtor,d to his Kingdom, caus'd the <hi>Queen,</hi> his daughter to be Slain, and alſo the chiefeſt Men of the Kingdom, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109194:39"/>pretext that they favour'd the Revolt, but it was truly to ſeiz their Goods to ſatisfy <hi>Gabinius:</hi> The <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> ſuffer'd all theſe Oppreſſions without Murmuring. But a few dayes after, a <hi>Roman</hi> Soldier, for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Cat by accident, was by the common People cut in peices on the place, for the violation done to the Country Gods, the authority of <hi>Ptolomy</hi> nor <hi>Gabinius</hi> not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſtrain them.</p>
            <p>Behold, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> at theſe words, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Caeſarion</hi> make a pauſe, a very ſtrange ſtory from firſt to laſt, and a ſtrangely various deſtiny, of this Unfortunate <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But pray let me know, if you pleaſe, if any thing elſe of Remarque befel him afterwards; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe known, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> but that a decay'd Knight of <hi>Rome,</hi> called * <hi>caius Rabirius Poſthumus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birio, Poſtumo.</hi>
               </note> who had furniſh'd or procur'd for him, ſeveral great ſums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney at <hi>Rome,</hi> when he was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his Kingdom, went to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand payment. This <hi>Prince</hi> told
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109194:39"/>him, he fear'd he ſhould never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſatisfie him, unleſs he would take the care and charge of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, by which means, he might by degrees reimburſe himſelf. But this Unfortunate Creditour, having accepted the offer for fear of loſing his Debt: The <hi>King</hi> ſoon after found a pretext to comit him Priſoner, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was one of the Antienteſt, and beſt of <hi>Caeſars</hi> friends; and that <hi>Pompey</hi> was alſo in a manner Caution for the Debt; the Money being lent in his preſence, and the Obligations paſt by his requeſt, at a Country-Houſe of his Neere <hi>Alba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Rabirius</hi> had the good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, not long after of eſcaping out of Priſon, recovering out of <hi>Egypt</hi> more miſerable than he went thither; and to compleat this Miſery, at his return to <hi>Rome,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Suet. <hi>in</hi> Claud. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> * he was judicially accuſed, to have aſſiſted <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> to corrupt the <hi>Senate,</hi> by the Sums of Money which he had lent him to this purpoſe, that he had forfeited his Honour of Knighthood, by the Imployment he had taken upon him
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109194:40"/>in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that he had correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſhared with <hi>Gabinius,</hi> in the Money that had been given him. The admirable diſcourſe <hi>Cicero</hi> made in his defence, and which we have yet remaining, is an Eternal Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the ingratitude and perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of this unworthy <hi>King;</hi> he dyed in the peaceable poſſeſſion of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> ſoon after this wicked Action, and about four Years after his Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: An Authentical Copy of his laſt Will was brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> to be depoſited in the publick Treaſury, having made the People of <hi>Rome</hi> his Executors, he conjru'd the <hi>Senat,</hi> in the name of all their Gods. (Caution of their Alliance) to favour the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, which he made of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to <hi>Ptolomy</hi> his eldeſt Son, who was afterwards ſirnamed <hi>Dennis,</hi> and to <hi>Cleopatra</hi> his eldeſt Daughter, whom he alſo enjoyned to Marry togeather, according to the cuſtom o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Country. It is alſo found, that <hi>Pompey</hi> was appointed Guardian to the young <hi>King</hi> by the People, who caus'd him to be ſo baſely Murder'd
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109194:40"/>fower Years after. This is in few words, <hi>ſaid Caeſarion,</hi> what we find upon Record, of the Life and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this <hi>King, Player</hi> on <hi>Flutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a Fidler, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> I think he was no foole. It ſeemes to me, all things confider'd, that he could not doe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his ill Fortune, and that he knew to be Cruel, Prodigal, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, for his own ends, as occaſion requir'd. But eſpecially I commend him, for engaging <hi>Gabinius</hi> in his Reſtoration, and were I not loath to be too troubleſome to you, I would deſire to be inform'd, what hapn'd to <hi>Gabinius afterwards:</hi> There hapn'd, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> nothing but what muſt needs come to paſs. <note place="margin">Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 39. <hi>Ad</hi> Att <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 16.</note> The Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats taking occaſion of his abſence, overrun and waſted all his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without any reſiſtance; and the Publicans of the Neighbour <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> being able no better than thoſe of <hi>Syria,</hi> by reaſon of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Robbers, not to convey the Money by land-carriage, which they were oblig'd to pay to the publick Treaſury at the time prefixt, they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109194:41"/>were forc'd to take up Money at <hi>Rome,</hi> at exceſſive Intereſt, to doe it, to their great Damage.</p>
            <p>The firſt News that was in <hi>Italy</hi> of <hi>Ptolomy</hi>'s Reſtauration, being brought to the Waters at <hi>Pouzzol,</hi> whither Recreation as well as Health invited much good company to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, it paſſed no ſooner from thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> but all the ſeveral ſorts of complaints and greivances, which were to be preferr'd againſt <hi>Gabini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> were, by the parties intereſted, diſpers'd about amongſt the People; ſo that it was reſolv'd, to inflict ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Puniſhments upon this <hi>Procon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul,</hi> at his returne to <hi>Rome.</hi> The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Senat</hi> were the forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in moving the Magiſtrats, to be inform'd of his Crimes, and there was nothing leſs than Death intended for him. He had not given the <hi>Senat</hi> advice of his expedition into <hi>Egypt,</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it would be worſe cenſur'd, than was that of <hi>Judea;</hi> and the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul Craſſus,</hi> who was to ſucceed him in <hi>Syria,</hi> having ſent one of his Leiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, to take poſſeſſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109194:41"/>in his name, <hi>Gabinius,</hi> to compleat his inſolency, refus'd to reſigne although his time was expir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>But how great ſoever this affront was to <hi>Craſſus,</hi> having a greater love for Money than Honour, <hi>Gabinius</hi> would have ſoon appeas'd him; in ſo much that <hi>Cicero</hi> ſometime after made a motion in the <hi>Senate,</hi> to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh again the Oracle of the <hi>Sybils,</hi> the more to exaſperate Mens minds; but <hi>Craſſus</hi> oppos'd himſelf thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as much as <hi>Pompey,</hi> and both of them were ſo diſpleas'd at <hi>Cicero,</hi> that they reviled him with his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. You may imagine how this Orator anſwer'd them, ſeeing he deſired no better Subject to inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that his reproach rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated than diſcourag'd him. To conclude, their <hi>Conſul-ſhip</hi> ending ſoon after, he cauſed the buſineſs to be brought under deliberation.</p>
            <p>The new <hi>Conſuls, Domitius</hi> and <hi>Appius,</hi> were not devoted unto <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus,</hi> as were the former; <hi>Domitius</hi> being promoted unto the Dignity
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109194:42"/>in ſpight of <hi>Pompey,</hi> was upon this ſcore his Enemy. <hi>Appius</hi> was his Ally, but he affected Popularity; and being moreover very Covetous, he was for compelling <hi>Gabinius</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his Protection: So it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre'd by common Conſent, that the Oracle ſhould be again publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Gabinius</hi> had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd from his Government, from the beginning of the Year <hi>DCXCIX.</hi> by <hi>Craſſus</hi> himſelf, who went the end of the precedent Year to take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, yet he made no haſt in coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> he would let the Peoples anger towards him to abate, and give time to his Friends to gain and corrupt his Judges and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, by the vaſt Sums of Money he had ſent before him to that purpoſe; but hearing that his delay rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated Mens minds againſt him than not, and that the <hi>Tribunes,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with his Stratagems, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to proceed to his Condemnation in his abſence; at laſt he ſet forwards, and on the way gave out that he was going to <hi>Rome,</hi> to demand a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109194:42"/>publick Triumph of the <hi>Senate</hi> for his two Expeditions into <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in effect, being arrived neer <hi>Rome</hi> the 19 of <hi>September,</hi> he enter'd not into the City to rights, but ſtai'd ſome Miles off, as the Generals were wont to doe, that pretended unto the Triumph, which was no ſooner known, but he was accus'd of three ſeveral Crimes, in the uſual form of Juſtice. Firſt againſt the State, for reſtoring the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Egypt. <note place="margin">Aſ. <hi>in</hi> Piſon <hi>ad</hi> Q. F. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1.2. &amp; 3.</note> Next</hi> of Intereſt, for the great Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions committed by him in <hi>Syria.</hi> And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> For buying of voices, when he was made <hi>Conſul</hi> 5 <hi>Yeares</hi> before.</p>
            <p>Theſe Accuſations, having ſoon made him relinquiſh the pretenſion of a Triumph, he came to <hi>Rome</hi> to defend himſelf the 27 of <hi>September,</hi> privatly in the night time; and in the pooreſt Equipage, that ever <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul</hi> did. Next day he appear'd, as he was aſſign'd before the <hi>Praetor,</hi> who was to be the Cheif Judg as to the Crime of State, he was a Perſon of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109194:43"/>known Worth and Integrity. Ten days after, he appear'd before the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> to give an account of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; but intending to go out after he had done it in a ſlight man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, he was ſtayed by the <hi>Conſuls,</hi> and at the ſame time the Publicans of <hi>Syria</hi> were call'd into the <hi>Senat,</hi> that he might anſwer their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaking in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, <hi>Gabinius</hi> defended himſelf by calling him Exile, with a low voice. But the whole <hi>Senat</hi> at this word riſing up as
'twere with one accord, impoſed ſilence on him, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans teſtified no leſs diſpleaſure, and the <hi>Conſul Appius,</hi> having alſo declar'd himſelf an Accuſer, named the Witneſſes and Acceſſorys of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binius</hi>'s Crimes, ſo that he could not anſwer a word.</p>
            <p>Fower dayes after he preſented himſelf before the People, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was ſo great, and the firſt reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his horrible Crimes ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that he had like to be ſtifled or torn to peices. Eſpecially a <hi>Tribune</hi> of the People, <hi>Cajus Memmius</hi> accus'd
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109194:43"/>him with ſo much vehemency, and to ſo general a liking, that he could not avoid being condemn'd to Death, or atl eaſt to perpetual Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that his Son, whom I mentioned to you before, being there preſent, ſupplicated <hi>Memmius</hi> to have compaſſion of him: But this <hi>Tribune</hi> tranſported with Pride, at the good ſucceſs of his enterpriſe, let the unfortunate Son lye at his feet, <note place="margin">Valer. Max. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> without taking the leaſt notice of him: The People being moved with ſome tenderneſs at ſuch a dutiful Object, the favourableneſs of the conjuncture gave courage to another <hi>Tribune,</hi> which he dared not do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, alſo being gain'd by <hi>Gabinius,</hi> to ſpake in his behalf, and made the Officer free him, that had already ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed on his Body.</p>
            <p>The People not deſiring to prevent the ordinary Judges in this Cauſe, as they were wont ſomtimes to doe; it was ſomtime after debated before them, and the Aſſembly was no leſs before the <hi>Praetors Tribunal,</hi> than it had been in the publick place: They
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109194:44"/>were to the number of Seventy, choſen partly out of the <hi>Senat,</hi> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the order of Knights, and of the <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the Treaſury. There were ſeveral accuſers; but he that ſpake in the behalf of the reſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd it ſo coldly, that every body ſuſpected he was corrupted by <hi>Gabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> as alſo the Judges that favour'd him. <hi>Pompey</hi> neglected no opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſerving him; he us'd all his endeavours to reconcile him to <hi>Cicero,</hi> and even to oblidge this Orator, to plead his cauſe, but to no purpoſe, and <hi>Cicero</hi> could not diſpenſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, from Witneſſing againſt him.</p>
            <p>It was urged in his behalf, that it was the intereſt of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to expel <hi>Archelaus</hi> out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> whoſe Fleet hinder'd the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation and Commerce of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the adjacent Seas, and gave all ſorts of aſſiſtance to Pyrats, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed all manner of Cruelties upon the Subjects of the Republick. It was alſo alleadged, this expedition was permitted unto <hi>Gabinius,</hi> by a Law whereof we have no Record;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109194:44"/>that at the worſt, the Oracle did not relate the preſent buſineſs, and that the matter hapned long before, in the Perſon of a former <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> whereof I made mention, who had alſo been expell'd out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and pray'd aſſiſtance of the <hi>Senat.</hi> But if the Oracle meant his Succeſſour,
<note place="margin">Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 39. Ad <hi>Att. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep.</hi> 4.</note> the <hi>Sybil</hi> not having expreſs'd what Puniſhment they deſerv'd, that ſhould reſtore this <hi>Prince,</hi> by force of Arms againſt its Prohibition, no body hath right to determin it.</p>
            <p>But with all theſe Evaſions <hi>Gabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> durſt not have conteſted, were it not for a rumor ſpread abroad, that <hi>Pompey</hi> was to be made Dictator: This Report was not without ſome collour. The Election of <hi>Conſuls</hi> being uſual about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> was deferr'd until towards the end of <hi>October,</hi> by ſeveral ſlights and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, that nothing regarded the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of <hi>Gabinius;</hi> and theſe hindran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not being likely to remove of themſelves, it was beleiv'd recourſe muſt be had to the means us'd at all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109194:45"/>times formerly in the like occaſions, which was to create a <hi>Dictator,</hi> whoſe unlimited power, was only able to reduce all perſons to their Duty.</p>
            <p>You may eaſily beleive on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, no body could more juſtly pretend to it than <hi>Pompey,</hi> although it's true, the <hi>Tribunes</hi> did not propoſe it in due form, but ſeveral Months after. <note place="margin">Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 40.</note> The Rumor that was ſpread abroad of it before hand, ſerv'd to intimidate the Judges, the greater part whereof were Perſons much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to him; and it was ſomthing ſtrange, that there were found, in this Conjuncture thirty-two, that had the honeſty and courage to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Gabinius,</hi> againſt Thirty-eight that declar'd him Innocent. <note place="margin">Ad <hi>Att. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>Ep.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Domitius Calvinius</hi> amongſt others, (through a partial Oſtentation, the like where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was never ſeen,) acquitted the Criminal by open voice, whereas he ſhould have given his Judgment by Scrutiny, as others did. Another roſe off the Bench, in ſight of all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, before the Seſſion was ended, as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109194:45"/>ſoon as ever the Voices were taken, to be the firſt carrier of the News to <hi>Pompey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See here, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> at theſe words, a happy Villian. Don't make too much haſt, <hi>ſaid Caeſarion,</hi> and ſtay till the end, ſeeing you deſire to know all. It wanted not much, but that the People had tore all the Judges to peices, at the firſt motion of their Rage. One of <hi>Gabinius</hi>'s freemen, that bore ſome command under him in <hi>Syria,</hi> being accus'd as one of his Acceſſaries, bore alſo the Puniſhment: This Wretches buſineſs was heard an hower after, before other Judges, he was condemn'd with the greater ſeverity, for Rage, that his Maſter had been accquitted and diſcharg'd.</p>
            <p>Dureing theſe Tranſactions the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Tyber</hi> overflow'd its banks on a ſuddain, with ſo great violence, <note place="margin">Dion. <hi>l.</hi> 39.</note> that it overthrew many Houſes and ſwept away many Perſons, as well at <hi>Rome,</hi> as in the adjacent parts. The People ſuppos'd there was ſomthing extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary in this Accident, and lookt upon it, as a Judgment from Heaven
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109194:46"/>upon them, for <hi>Gabinius</hi> and his Judges, having ſlighted the Orracle of the <hi>Sibyls.</hi> I told you, he ſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd, for three ſeveral Crimes: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore accquitted for that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the State, he was proſecuted for his Extortions, by the ſame <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune Memmius,</hi> which had ſo ſharply proſecuted him before the People; by <hi>Tiberius Nero,</hi> Father of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> of that name; and by <hi>Cajus</hi> and <hi>Lucius,</hi> Brothers to the ſame <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi> that was afterwards <hi>Tryumvir,</hi> and that commanded his <hi>Cavalry.</hi> The great <hi>Cato</hi> (who, I told you had the intervew with <hi>Ptolomey</hi> at <hi>Rhodes</hi>) preſided in this Judgment in quallity of <hi>Praetor.</hi> He had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpos'd, and for that reaſon Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was deferr'd, the Judges were alſo chang'd, but <hi>Gabinius</hi> thought himſelf ſo fully accquitted, that he took not the paines nor trouble, to gaine them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pompey</hi> having ſtill the charge of the <hi>Corn</hi> buſineſs, was abſent from <hi>Rome,</hi> repairing the dammages made by the Inundation of the River, which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:109194:46"/>had ravadged, deſtroy'd, and ſpoil'd, vaſt quanteties of Grain, and the moſt fertile Feilds of all <hi>Italy.</hi> But recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving advice of the danger <hi>Gabinius</hi> was in, he came as near the City as he could, to try to ſave him once more, and his Office not permitting him to enter into the City, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled the People without the Walls, and harrangu'd them to that effect. He publickly read Letters from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> wherein he recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Gabinius</hi> unto him, with all the affection that could be, and for the laſt Remedy, he prevail'd with <hi>Cicero,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dion. 39 Valer. Max. <hi>l.</hi> 4. c. 2.</note> to plead for him; for which this Orator was ſurnamed <hi>Turn-coate</hi> to reproach either his weakneſs, or inconſtancy.</p>
            <p>I perceive then, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> at theſe words, <hi>Pompey</hi> was as zealous a Friend, as <hi>Ciſero</hi> was a weak Enemy. <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey, reply'd Ceſarion,</hi> had, as all ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Men have, the vulgar Maxim, which almoſt comprehends the skill of rhe Pollititians of theſe times; to be a good Friend and a cruel Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, without any Judgment in chooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:109194:47"/>Friends or Enemies. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor they, need be oblidg'd, to venture ſo far for their Friends, if there were none but good Men. It's only for bad Men, that theſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary endeavours of Credit and Authority need be uſed; and how bad a buſineſs ſoever befals an honeſt Man, the regular forms are always ſufficient, to bring him off. So that this reſolvedneſs, and great zeale, which is ſhewn for defending and protecting vitious Perſons, is ſo far from being Praiſe-worthy, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more odious, and deteſtable; ſeeing that in effect, it hath only ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſt or Vanity for its Motive; and Injuſtice for its Scope.</p>
            <p>Beware of Digreſſion, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> and pray let me know, if <hi>Gabinius</hi> was condemn'd or accquitted, this ſecond time. He was condemn'd, <hi>ſaid Caeſarion,</hi> to perpetual Banniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his goods confiſcated, notwithſtanding the power of <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey,</hi> and Eloquence of <hi>Cicero.</hi> But <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> eſteeming him one of the beſt Commanders in <hi>Rome,</hi> making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109194:47"/>Maſter of the Republick ſix <hi>Years</hi> after, he recal'd him out of Banniſhment, and gave him the Command of a little Army in <hi>Illyria,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caeſar <hi>de</hi> Bell. Allex. App. <hi>in</hi> Illiric.</note> where he was routed by the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> of the Country, and being forc'd to fly to <hi>Salonia,</hi> he there end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his dayes, not long after.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Day.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:109194:48"/>
            <head>CAESARION. The <hi>Third</hi> Day.</head>
            <p>IF you did not know as well as I, that Nature had endow'd your Friend, with two of the moſt incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Talents</hi> in the World, I mean, a prodigious Memory, and an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Judgment; you would ſcarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive, that he recited to me <hi>extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> the Hiſtories that I have related to you. Although I had heard much of his great Accompliſhments, yet I was not a little ſurpris'd, for he look'd not paſt three or four times, on his Books and Papers, to make ſo long a <hi>Narration,</hi> and he had all he ſaid, as ready in his mind, as if he related to me his own particular concerns. I was only deſirous to be ſatisfi'd, where 'twas, that he read and found
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109194:48"/>ſo many conſiderable things, as he mention'd to me, and which I do not remember, to have Read in the <hi>Greek</hi> nor <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtorians, which wrote of thoſe Times. His demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in all things, were very modeſt and obliging: meeting him the next day, as I walked upon a Terraſs that fronted his Houſe towards the Valley, I could not forbear asking him, and he ſoon anſwer'd me, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Book</hi> into my hand, that he was Reading, as if he ſhould ſay, that 'twas from thence he collected all, that I thought he had invented in his own Brain. I open'd the <hi>Book</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry haſtily, but my curioſity was not much ſatisfi'd, when I ſaw it was nothing but <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>As the Reading of thoſe Epiſtles at the Univerſity, made no great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on my mind, ſo I was the more ſurpris'd at what I ſaw; he began to laugh at my aſtoniſhment, and ſaid unto me, that I ſhould not be troubl'd, that it was not me he blam'd but my Tutors, becauſe it was their fault more than mine, if I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:109194:49"/>had not relliſh'd the ſweetneſs of the moſt pretious remains of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. That he had often admired in himſelf, how thoſe Docters could pretend to know, the nice and fineſt things in the World, when they did not underſtand them, and that I ſhould be no leſs ſurpris'd, if I would but Read over thoſe Letters with him, that had been ſo irkſom to me heretofore. You may well beleive, I took him at his word. Having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore open'd the firſt <hi>Book</hi> of thoſe to <hi>Atticus,</hi> he Read out two or three of them, which treated of the ſame Matter, and as I intimated to him, the great deſire I had to heare him on this Subject, he delay'd ſattisfying me no longer, but till ſuch time, as we retir'd into the Cloſet, where he ſo pleaſantly entertain'd me, the Day before.</p>
            <p>What delights me moſt of all, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> of the practiſe of the Antients, is the regularity of their Friendſhip, it is the only thing wherein they moſt of all Excel us, and wherein we leaſt ſtrive to equal them. On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109194:49"/>ſhould any one at this time practiſe this regularity, he would be eſteem'd Ridiculous; the beſt of his friends would admire him, for the infinite advantages, of being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd after this manner, whileſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would impudently deride it. But all in general would look upon him as a friendly <hi>Tyrant,</hi> if he expected they ſhould be as regular towards him, as he is punctual to them.</p>
            <p>It was not ſo that Men liv'd in <hi>Greece,</hi> in the days of <hi>Zenophon,</hi> this Regularity ſo little practis'd amongſt us, was then lookt upon as an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable Duty: All aſpir'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as a quality abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for every body to have; they boaſted of it, as of the moſt ſhining Vertues. <hi>They Dyed,</hi> ſaid this Illuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Athenian,</hi> making the Elogy of the <hi>Greek</hi> Captains his companions, that had been perfidiouſly Maſſacred by the Treacherous <hi>Perſians. <note place="margin">Zen. <hi>Ret. of</hi> 10. m. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> They dyed, having liv'd without reproach, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in War or Friendſhip.</hi> Who in our times, dare uſe the like comenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in the Funeral Solemnities of our Generals?</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:109194:50"/>
            <p>There ſeems to be as much Heat and Vigour in Friendſhip now a days, as there was formerly, but there is not ſo much Tenderneſs. It has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd in our dayes, Actions of as great Fidelity, Liberality, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage as ever; but I queſtion, if there can be found, ſo many inſtances of Gentleneſs and Patience, ſo frequently ſeen amongſt the Antients, for the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and even the unjuſt reproaches of their Friends? for the modeſt complacency, which they ſhew'd for the boundleſs Paſſions, of them whom they lov'd, and to conclude, the ſame punctuality, the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and the ſame concernedneſs, for all that regards our Friends, as we would, that they ſhould have for Us.</p>
            <p>It may be, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we Love leſs than they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, but only we have leſs Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Judgment. You need only, ſaid <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> but compare the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of our times, with the Friends, to diſcern the Invalidneſs of your Anſwer. Lovers, do they not daily
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:109194:50"/>do for their Miſtreſſes, that which true Friendſhip ſhould do for his Friend? Have they not for them all the Care, Dilligence, and Reſpect that can be deſir'd? A Soul truly touch'd with a lively Simpathy, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wants Motives to follow its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations; there is common Effects of this ſeen in vulgar Perſons. They ſeem to be inſpir'd with ſome new Genius, when they begin to be in Love, they appear Witty beyond their Natural Endowments, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in what regards their Paſſion. What Love Operates in mean Souls, not Friendſhip do much more, in Perſons of a Nobler make, if it be Sincere? If it do's not at all times diſcharge its Function, may it not well be concluded that 'tis not Sincere, and that 'tis kept up in the occaſions wherein it Opperates, by ſome other Motive, to which it only lends it's Name.</p>
            <p>But now 'tis high time to tell you, wherefore I took occaſion to make thoſe reflections; <hi>Atticus</hi> having been Arbitrat in a certain Buſineſs, of a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109194:51"/>Friend both of his and <hi>Cicero</hi>'s, this Friend was not very well pleas'd with the Judgment made by <hi>Atticus,</hi> in the matter. And by what follows, it ſeems he had no great cauſe to be ſattisfy'd. For <hi>Atticus</hi> going into <hi>Greece</hi> a little after, he wrote to <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> upon this Subject in theſe Terms, as ſoon as he was arriv'd at <hi>Athens. If any body be diſpleas'd with me, it is your part to appeaſe them. It was needleſs,</hi> anſwer'd Cicero, <hi>that you ſhould bid me do it, for I endeavour'd it before; this party is very much offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at you, I omitted nothing that could be ſaid on this ſubject, but I did not think it convenient to preſs him any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until I knew your mind,</hi> whether you deſire it or not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quod ſcribis, etiam ſi cujus animus in te eſſet offenſior, a me recolligi oportere. Quid dicas? Neque id neglexi. Sed eſt miro quodam modo affectus Ego autem quae dicenda fuerunt de te non preterii. Quid autem contendendem eſſet, ex tua putabam voluntate ſtatuere oportere Ad</hi> Atticum. l. 1. <hi>Fp.</hi> 5.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:109194:51"/>
            <p>You will grant that any body elce beſides <hi>Gicero,</hi> would not have ſtay'd for a new Order, and would have thought themſelves ſufficiently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powr'd, by what <hi>Atticus</hi> had writ, to deale with their common Friend, perhaps more than <hi>Atticus</hi> would have deſir'd. This daily fall's out, becauſe moſt Men rather aſpire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Commendation, than to ſerve thoſe well that do Employ them, in concerning themſelves only ſo far as they have a mind; nothing is more dangerous, than to ſeek this kind of of Serviſe of ones Friend, for moſt do more than they are deſir'd, and which is worſt of all, one dares not complain, for fear of being blam'd by the World, becauſe of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended good meaning, which in my Judgment, is the moſt frivolous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in the World. For every body eaſily perceives, when they paſs the bounds of their commiſſion, and one queſtions in paſſing it, if what we doe, will be well reſented or not? and in this reſpect, it is a kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs to do it. Becauſe one
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109194:52"/>runs a Riſque of diſobliging a Friend, in ſeeming to goe about to ſerve him. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quam ſi ad me per ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſeris intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, me neque di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem eſſes, voluiſſe quam tu eſſes neque negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorem fore quam tu velis. Ille noſter amicus ſane tibi iratus eſt. Hoc ſi quanti tu eſtimes, ſciam tum quid mihi ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſit ſcire poſſim.</hi> 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cicero</hi> was too brave a Perſon, to fall into ſuch an Error. <hi>If you write unto me,</hi> continues he, <hi>how far I ſhall proceed you, ſhall find, that I will not be more haſty in accommodating you than you deſire, nor more backward than you would have me be.</hi> And in another Letter writ a little after, not having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved anſwer unto the former. * <hi>Our Friend,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>again, is very angry with with you; if you let me know how much you care for it, I can tell what meanes to uſe to appeaſe him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He knew very well, that how ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoever the pretext of Reconcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friends is, yet he ought not to paſs the intention of him, that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadg'd him in the buſineſs, and deſir'd the accomodation, on ſuch and ſuch Terms, but not on any Terms what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. He had not the Ambition ſo common amongſt us, to pretend to impoſe upon his Friends, in what they lik'd or lik'd not, but reſted ſatisfi'd to reconcile them. Moſt Men doe now a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:109194:52"/>dayes advance themſelves into <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogues,</hi> and affect a higher degree of Wiſdom and Knowledg, which is the greateſt Bane of true Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>How many be there, that Act in a Buſineſs according to the mind of him that Employ them, when ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, they think they ought to Act quite contrary? It were ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if in this Conſideration they would deſire wholly to be excus'd, but ther's very few, that Act with ſuch freedom. On the contrary, either to be thought not to forſake their Friends in their neceſſity, or that they fear the buſineſs being done by othe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs, it may have ſucceſs contrary to their advice, the moſt part continue to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, even when they are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd, and pretending to govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs as they were intruſted, which yet they approve not off, they endeavour what they can under hand, to let the buſineſs fall, thereby the better to Juſtify their own Sentiments. And if it be diſcover'd that they have Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed contrary to directions, and to what they promis'd, they never
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:109194:53"/>want Reaſons to ſhew, that one ſhould approve of their Conduct; but this is not much to the purpoſe: Or if they do not the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of what they were deſir'd, they ſatisfy themſelves barely, with acting only ſo far, as that it might be ſaid, that they employ'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the buſineſs, and how ill ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they acted, they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves discharg'd in ſaying, that one can never mind ev'ry thing, or that they thought they did all for the better.</p>
            <p>True Friendſhip is never redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſuch a <hi>non-plus,</hi> it is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Spring of Induſtry, it can do nothing by halves, and it holds that for ill done, which might be better done, but more eſpecially it appears admirable in buſineſs, wherein Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt are concern'd, not to explain it any farther. Nothing is eaſier, then to make him paſs by what one has no Mind to diſcover, and although one expoſe not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by declaring ones Mind, he is not at all diſpleas'd at it, and he acts
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109194:53"/>no leſs Diligence, than if one had fully and freely committed ones ſelf to his diſcretion. Beſides, he is not ſatisfy'd with himſelf, no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he ſatisfy's thoſe for whom he acts: he cannot admit of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Intereſt in what he do's, but that of his Friend; he neglects him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the better and more perfectly to underſtand his Friends Deſign and Paſſion. Therefore it falls out, that many times he knows better than they, what they would, and what they would not have done, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridles their oppoſite thoughts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are moſt agitated, and diſcerns ſometimes better than they do, what they moſt deſire, and what at laſt ſhall be moſt predominant.</p>
            <p>Falſe Friendſhip, on the contrary, is always diſſatisfied with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that 'tis employ'd, it is always ſelf-conceited; it never fails of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome private Intereſt in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs wherein it is employ'd, how little ſoever it regards him; it has always ſome private End, that it dares not own; It holds with the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:109194:54"/>Letter when it ſhould with the Sence, and commonly ſeeks ſome contrary meaning, when 'tis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to keep to the Literal Senſe. Beſides it has ever either ill Read or ill Heard, and things are never plainly enough expreſt.</p>
            <p>One cannot, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> ramble more pleaſantly than you do, for we have almoſt loſt ſight of <hi>Atticus;</hi> and to ſay the truth, I would willingly hear farther of him. <hi>Cicero,</hi> repy'd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> receiv'd Letters from him, ſoon after the Letter I formerly mention'd, and he reply'd to him in theſe Terms. <hi>I promiſe you to pacifie our Friend, and it may be ingage him alſo, to be wholly yours. I endeavour'd it before of my own accord, but now I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by your Letter, that you earneſtly deſire it, I will employ my ſelf more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently therein, and will preſs him more earneſtly than I did. You need not doubt but he is highly diſpleas'd with you, but as I know that he has no great reaſon for it, I dare undertake to pacifie and to diſpoſe him as I liſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tibi de noſtro amico placando, aut
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109194:54"/>etiam plane reſtituendo polliceor. Quod ego, etſi mea ſponte ante facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam, eo nunc tamen, &amp; agam ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius, &amp; contendam ab illo vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, quod tamen ex Epiſtola volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ejus rei tuam perſpicere vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. Hoc te intelligere volo, pergra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter illum eſſe offenſum. Sed quia nullam video gravem ſubeſſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, magnopere confido illum fore in officio, &amp; in noſtra poteſtate. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>ad</hi> Atticum.</p>
            <p>You may ſee what were <hi>Cicero</hi>'s hopes, but he was miſtaken, and you need not be ſurpris'd at it, for ther's no body but may be miſtaken, if they do not fully know the ground and bottom of a Buſineſs, and one is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound to judge aright of what one is inform'd; <hi>after having us'd all endeavours,</hi> ſay's he <hi>to</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus, <hi>very far from ſetling you in his thoughts as you had been before, I could not ſo much as gather from him, the cauſe of his Strangeneſs. For whatſoever he ſay's of your Arbitration, and of the other things, I knew before wherewith he was diſſatisfi'd at your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, there is ſomething elſe he
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109194:55"/>ſticks at more than all that; the which neither your</hi> Letters, <hi>nor my Mediation cannot reconcile, as well as you may do your ſelf at your return hither, not only by Converſation, but alſo by your Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging wayes, that is, if you think it worth your while. And do not think ſtrange, that I dare not promiſe any Kindneſs from him, having intimated to you in my laſt, that I us'd all my endeavours. You cannot beleive, how much ſtranger he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me than formerly, and perſiſts more in his Obſtinacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cum omnia feciſſem, non modo eam voluntatem ejus, quae fuerat er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga te, recuperare non potui, verum ne cauſam quidem elicere immutatae voluntatis. Tametſi jactat ille qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem illud ſuum arbitrium, &amp; ea quae jam tum cum aderas offendere ejus animum intelligebam. Tamen habet quiddam profecto quod magis in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo ejus inſederit, quod neque E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolae tuae, neque noſtra Allegatio tam poteſt facile delere, quam tu praeſens, non modo oratione, ſed illo tuo vultu familiari, tolles, ſi modo
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109194:55"/>tanti putabis, id quod ſi me audies, &amp; ſi humanitati tuae conſtare voles certe putabis. Ac ne illud mirere cum ego antea ſignificarem tibi per lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, me ſperare eum in noſtra proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate fore, nunc idem videar diffidere. Incredibile eſt, quantum mihi vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur illius voluntas obſtinatior, &amp; in hac iracundia obfirmatior. 10.</p>
            <p>You ſee by this, that <hi>Cicero</hi>'s mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration was very diſcreet, and you perceive that his Friend being irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable, <hi>Atticus</hi> it may be would not have gone any farther to have pacifi'd him, and therefore would have had juſt cauſe to blame <hi>Cicero,</hi> had <hi>Cicero</hi> done it without his expreſs Order.</p>
            <p>But wherefore would not this Man, <hi>reply'd I</hi> at theſe words, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his greateſt Cauſe of diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Atticus?</hi> You muſt not, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> wonder at that; the moſt Sincere and the moſt Senſible are they which ſay leaſt; becauſe they are Clear, Conſtant, and Free from making feigned or frivolous
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:109194:56"/>Excuſes. Now to what purpoſe is it to diſcover a thing, where there is not a Salve or Remedy for it.</p>
            <p>Moreover the greatneſs of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury is never well known, but by him that gave it, and by him that receiv'd it, foraſmuch as it depends on the Circumſtance, wherein the party offended was, when he receiv'd it; to know to what degree he was concern'd, and how far the Offender knew his Senſibility. And from hence it happens, that the moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Injuries be thoſe, that ſometimes ſeem the leaſt, to thoſe that have not receiv'd them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there be things that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be fully explain'd without Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing others, which it were better to hide and conceal. Therefore, thoſe, which have committed ſuch Extravagancies, do ſo often dare thoſe to Publiſh them, to whom they have done them, knowing very well the Parties offended will rather endeavour to Conceal them if they be Wiſe, but if they be ſo imprudent to diſcover themſelves, they are ſoon
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109194:56"/>puniſh'd by their own Folly, by gratifying others, in declaring what they have ſuffer'd; this pleaſure is ſo great and pleaſing to corrupt Minds, that inſtead of being aſham'd to publiſh their wickedneſs, they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it, and do manifeſt, that this very declaring of it is the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing the Triumph of their Spleen and Malice.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> ther's nothing more generally blam'd, than this unwillingneſs, of owning the diſpleaſure, one harbours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Enemy. You ſee how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> that at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain times, ther's nothing more juſt and prudent, than this kind of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinateneſs.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Cicero</hi> adds afterwards, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sed haec aut ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur cum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris, aut ei moleſta e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, in utro cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa erit.</hi> ibid.</note> 
               <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues he,</hi> will more ſurpriſe you. <hi>But,</hi> concludes he, <hi>either you will compoſe theſe matters when you arrive here, or which ever of you both are in the wrong, it will fare the worſe with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe which ſeems ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, was the very Truth it ſelf. The Reputation of <hi>Atticus</hi>'s
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109194:57"/>Wiſdom and Probity was ſo well ſetled, that no body in <hi>Rome</hi> would ſcarce have queſtion'd it, although his proceedings, at all times, were not the faireſt.</p>
            <p>He was one of thoſe kind of <hi>Sparks,</hi> that was neither Eminent by Birth, nor by Office, nor by any extraordinary Parts, but made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be talkt of by an affected way of Living, and of being admitted into Great mens company, who, for the moſt part, are not the hardeſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. For which purpoſe, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have ſtore of Wealth, and a great deal of Wit; to be born with a temper incapable of violent Paſſions, neither good nor bad, and with a great ſtock of indifferency for Truth and Juſtice, that can ſee theſe divine Virtues violated, and be able to violate them, when 'tis for ones Intereſt. It is requiſit, to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally neither a Deceiver nor Unjuſt, that one ſhould, in moſt occaſions, practiſe theſe Virtues in ſhew and ſeemingly, becauſe in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it is more uſeful, to be Juſt and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:109194:57"/>Sincere, than to be otherwiſe. Alſo it is requiſit, to appear a Friend e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually alike to all ſorts of perſons, and not to be ſo truly to any body. Not much to frequent ones Equals, and neither to deſpiſe them. With theſe qualities, it is an eaſie matter to inſinuate into great Mens compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, eſpecially if ones behaviour be not Offenſive.</p>
            <p>If ſuch a perſon as this will alſo force himſelf to flatter great Perſons in their follies, wherewith they are moſt pleas'd, praiſe them for quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which they really have, and for which every body blames them, and for thoſe they think they have, and that every body knows they have not, how do they delight in ſuch a Perſon, and how do they cry him up? But eſpecially, if he holds in favour with thoſe, that are at enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt themſelves, then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes alike uſeful to both party's, they both vie in his commendation, and others, ſeeing Perſons ſo divided, agree in admiring him; it's preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleiv'd, it can only be pure Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109194:58"/>that can ſo unite them, and ſo conceive a good opinion of him, which,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si liberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueſti, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum putatis. ep.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 5. ad fam. <hi>Sanctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerrimi illahuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina.</hi>
               </note> diffuſing abroad, do's inſenſib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly create this ſhadow of Reputation, wherewith thoſe are deluded, that do really want it themſelves.</p>
            <p>Such a kind of Perſon was <hi>Atticus,</hi> but his <hi>Antagoniſt</hi> was a Man of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Temper, and of a make altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Solid and Sincere, as that of <hi>Atticus</hi> was Forc'd and Artificial. He was call'd <hi>Lucius Lucceius,</hi> and was of a very good Family. He wrote the Hiſtory of his times, with much Honour and Eloquence, as may be judg'd by <hi>Cicero</hi>'s deſiring him to write that of his <hi>Conſulſhip</hi> apart, <hi>and with that Freedom and Sincerity, which was ſo Natural to him.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</note> The ſame <hi>Cicero</hi> in a publick Act ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauds <hi>The integrity of his life, his virtue, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Meher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule vir optimus &amp; mihi amiciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> ad Att. <hi>l.</hi> 1. Ep. 17.</note> goodneſs, and learning, with a greatneſs,</hi> that cannot be the leaſt queſtion'd; eſpecially conſidering, that writing to <hi>Atticus</hi> himſelf about their difference, he cannot forbear to call the ſame <hi>Lucceius, a very honeſt Man, and his very good Friend.</hi> He was
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:109194:58"/>afterwards Competitor with <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Bibulus</hi> for the <hi>Conſulſhip,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sueto. <hi>c.</hi> 19. ad Att, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 16. <hi>Optima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, viri boni</hi> ad Att. <hi>paſſim.</hi>
               </note> and was refus'd it for no other reaſon, but for Correſponding with <hi>Caeſar</hi> againſt <hi>Bibulus.</hi> For this Familiarity made him be ſuſpected by the <hi>great Men,</hi> which were call'd the <hi>Honeſt Party,</hi> and declar'd Enemies to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> But as they could not exclude this great Man, and that 'twas of great Moment to the Common-Wealth, that he ſhould not have the <hi>Colleague</hi> he deſir'd, they us'd ſuch extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means to fruſtrate <hi>Lucceius,</hi> that at laſt they effected their deſires, and and choſe <hi>Bibulus</hi> in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>It appears that failing in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he quitted all farther preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, doubting the ſucceſs, by reaſon of his many great and powerful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and in all likelihood, the very great ſincerity of Life, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd and practis'd, made him give over the Correſpondence he had maintain'd with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he imploy'd him not in the Civil Wars, as he did all his other friends, and kept himſelf all that time in
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109194:59"/>the Country, or privately in <hi>Rome</hi> at his Study, or other Domeſtick Affairs.</p>
            <p>But if you deſire to know him more particularly, than by what I have already ſaid, you may be pleas'd to read a Letter which he wrote to <hi>Cicero,</hi> upon the death of his dear Daughter <hi>Tullia.</hi> Methinks it ſhews ſo much tenderneſs, wiſdom and diſcretion, that I was much pleas'd in Tranſlating it. At theſe words <hi>Caeſarion</hi> opening a little Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript full of Tranſlations made by him, which I ſince copy'd out; I there read this which follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:109194:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CCEI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> his Letter to <hi>CICERO.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF you are in Health, I am glad of it; for my part I am much after one rate, or rather ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe than I uſe to be. I went to viſit you, but was ſurpris'd to hear you were gone out of <hi>Rome</hi> as ſoon as you had left me, and am ſtill ſo, not imagining what ſhould oblige you thereto. If you are beſt pleas'd with privacy and retirement to write and ſtudy after your uſual manner, I rejoyce at it, and am very far from bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming you; for one can neither be better employ'd in theſe ſad times wherein we live, nor in more flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and happy days, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a rare Genius as yours, which ſeeks a little reſpite from the trouble of your great Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that always produceth ſomething delightful unto others, and glorious for your ſelf. But if
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109194:60"/>it be wholy to give your ſelf up to grief, as you did here, that you are retir'd, then am I ſenſibly concern'd for you, becauſe you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. But if you ſuffer me to ſpeak my mind, I cannot approve your conduct. For can it be, that you, whoſe judgement penetrates the moſt hidden things, don't perceive that your continual ſorrowing do's you no good at all, and that you only increaſe your affliction, which your diſcretion ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mitigate. But if I cannot prevail with you by my perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I beg it of you in kindneſs, and by all the reſpect you have for me. I conjure you to give off this doleful kind of living, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the enjoyment of your friends; or if you deſire to live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, in living at leaſt with your ſelf, as you were wont to do before your misfortune, do ſo. If you are diſpleas'd with me for my good will, I am ſorry to have troubled you, yet I would fain divert you from the courſe you
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:109194:60"/>take. Being moved with theſe two contrary paſſions, I hope you will either grant what I deſire, if you can, or that you will pardon my importunity if you cannot. <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <head>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CCEI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CICERONI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SI vales bene eſt, ego valeo ſicut ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo, paululo tamen etiam deterius quam ſoleo. Te requiſivi ſaepius ut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derem. Romae, quia poſtea non fuiſti quam a me diſceſſeras, miratus ſum; quod item nunc miror. Non habeo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quae te res hinc maxime retrahat. Si ſolitudine delectere cum ſcribas, &amp; aliquid agas eorum, quorum conſueſti, gaudeo, neque reprehendo conſilium tuum. Nam nihil iſto poteſt eſſe jucundius, non modo miſeris his temporibus &amp; luctuoſis, ſed etiam tranquillis &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis: praeſertim, vel animo defatigato tuo, qui nunc requietem quaerat ex mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis occupationibus, vel erudito, qui ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per aliquid ex ſe promat quod alios de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectet, teipſum laudibus illuſtret. Sin
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109194:61"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="111" facs="tcp:109194:61"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:109194:62"/>autem ſicut hic dum eras, &amp; lacrymis &amp; triſtitiae te tradidiſti, doleo, quia doles &amp; angere: nec poſſum te (ſi concedis quod ſentimus ut liberius dicamus) non accuſare. Quid enim? tu ſolus aperta non videbis, qui propter acumen occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima perſpicis? Tu non intelliges, to querelis quotidianis nihil proficere? non intelliges duplicari ſollicitudines, quas elevare tua te prudentia poſtulat. Quod ſi non poſſumus aliquid proficere ſuadendo, gratia contendimus; &amp; ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando, ſi quid noſtra cauſa vis, ut iſtis te moleſtiis laxes, &amp; ad convictum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum redeas, &amp; ad conſuetudinem, vel noſtram communem, vel tuam ſolius, ac propriam. Cupio non obtundere te ſi non delectere noſtro ſtudio: cupio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrere ne permaneas in incaepto. Quum dua res iſtae contrariae me conturbent, ex quibus, aut in altera mihi velim, ſi potes, obtemperes, aut in altera non offendas, Vale.</hi> L. 5. Ad famil. Ep. 14.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>See here, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> (having done reading) a very obliging advice, and I cannot tell how a perſon of ſuch ſingular merit could be refus'd,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109194:62"/>being in the right. Yet there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more frequently ſeen, reply'd <hi>Caeſarion.</hi> The greateſt merits were not moſt eſteem'd in corrupt ages, as was the laſt of that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth. There ſhin'd ſo many virtues amongſt that glorious people for the ſpace of ſix hundred years, that it could not be but ſome footſteps of them remained in the age we ſpeak of. But in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as craft and vice, which neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily attend the greatneſs of World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Empire, had attained unto their higheſt pitch: Art had in moſt things ſubverted Nature, and the little, but pretious remainder, of ancient ſimplicity and integrity of former ages, being mixt with much deceit and ſeeming virtue, became ſo much the more odious, as that it put on the reſemblance of truth it ſelf.</p>
            <p>In all ages Truth has been called a <hi>Chimaera</hi> by thoſe that are not able to underſtand it, and thoſe which do comprehend it, not puting it in practiſe, through malice, ſpeak
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:109194:63"/>ſlightly of it, and give it the worſt character they can. It were well if it were quit for not pleaſing them; but as they cannot but admire it in their ſoul, they continue not in an indifferency, but go on to hate it, becauſe naturally men hate what they Eſteem very much, but cannot Love.</p>
            <p>How is't poſſible, ſay they, to live with perſons that never will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd with thoſe they have once differ'd, that forgive not their friends, that have no regard for their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, nor for their intreaties; that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſuch care and obſervance, that good Maſters would not require from their Slaves; that do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their own concerns, and that will not ſuffer their friends to take the care which they ought to take their ownſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cicero</hi> might have ſaid all this againſt <hi>Lucceius</hi> upon his obſtinacy in not agreeing with <hi>Atticus,</hi> but he knew very well, that 'tis only thoſe which eaſily differ, that are ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled again. That offences which
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:109194:63"/>deſerve but little notice to be taken of them, being received from indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſons, are mortal injuries when they proceed from a perſon that one loves, or of thoſe by whom we think we deſerve to be loved; no body is a better judge of advice, than him to whom it is given; that there are requeſts which be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious as well as juſt: That one may expect from their friends, the ſame care and kindneſs as one hath for them. And to conclude, it is for the moſt part a kind of reproof, rather than ſign of friendſhip, to concern one ſelf in others affairs, whether they will or not.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Rules whereby <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> governed himſelf with his friends. But there were but very few that were ſo virtuous as he was; as the friendſhip of <hi>Atticus</hi> was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial, crafty, and ſuted, and adapted to the Commerce of the World; ſo that of <hi>Lucceius</hi> was pure and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and altogether unfit for the World: It is not ſtrange therefore, that <hi>Atticus</hi> his humour was more
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109194:64"/>taking, and oftentimes procur'd him an applauſe that he did not really deſerve.</p>
            <p>For the World do's uſually judge of affairs by the perſons, inſtead of judging by the things themſelves, for it requires ſome pains to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine a buſineſs, and 'tis a trouble which men do not willingly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go; whereas there's no pains in judging of affairs thereafter as one is affected more or leſs with the perſon it concerns. Moreover when once one is ſetled in a fancy, one natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhuns knowing what might change our opinion, becauſe men don't care to know that they have been deceived.</p>
            <p>There is therefore no cauſe to wonder why <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid, <hi>That whoever it was that was in the right, either</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus <hi>or</hi> Lucceius, <hi>their conteſt would only prove prejudicial to</hi> Lucceius <hi>in the Worlds eſteem.</hi> Although <hi>Cicero</hi> wrote ſo plainly to <hi>Atticus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in ſuppoſing he might be in the wrong; to <hi>Atticus</hi> I ſay, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways boaſted to be in the right. I
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:109194:64"/>make no doubt, but knowing him as I do, this ſuppoſition toucht him to the quick, though perhaps he was glad at the heart that <hi>Cicero</hi> own'd, as he did by this Diſcourſe, that his reputation was ſetled to ſuch a degree, that it might be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, even without reaſon, againſt a man of that worth <hi>Lucceius</hi> was of; and in all likelihood it was to give him this ſecret pleaſure, that <hi>Cicero,</hi> who underſtood him very well, wrote to him after this manner.</p>
            <p>Yet I have one requeſt more to make to you, reply'd I, ſeeing <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarion</hi> ſilent. It is to know if this grudge laſted always, it is not known, ſaid he, how they were reconciled. But it appears by <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>'s Letters, that they viſited each other familiarly twelve years after. That's a thing often ſeen when one has to do with a man of <hi>Atticus</hi> his temper. How much ſoever one is perſwaded of their perfidiouſneſs, they'l make themſelves no ſtrangers, and wanting no excuſes of one ſort or other, they employ ſo many
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:109194:65"/>friends to compoſe matters, that at laſt one is forc't to comply: for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly perſons are more inclinable to the Offendor, than to the Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the malignity of nature, being delighted at the ſeeing and ſuffering of ill, never fails, in theſe Occaſions, to incline to him that gave the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to the prejudice of him that received it, under the ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of making Peace.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs I cannot tell but the open Enmity of <hi>Atticus</hi> had been leſs hurtful to <hi>Lucceius</hi> than their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: for <hi>Atticus</hi> never acted but through reſpect of his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt, and would never have been ſo deſirous of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had he not believ'd that <hi>Luccei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his Enmity would have been to his diſadvantage; not but that his alſo might have been hurtful to <hi>Lucceius;</hi> but there was this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be made, that their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation did abſolutely remove the diſadvantage which <hi>Atticus</hi> might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by this Enmity, becauſe <hi>Luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceius</hi> could not be reconcil'd but with
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:109194:65"/>a truly good intent, whereas there was great cauſe to think that <hi>Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> would not be any truer to him after reconciliation, than he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their rupture, eſpecially being netl'd by the long refuſal <hi>Lucceius</hi> made of being accommodated, and by the ſecret reproaches of his own Conſcience, wherewith the moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons (do they what they can to ſuppreſs them) are as often tormented, as the moſt ignorant ſort of men.</p>
            <p>By what I had ever heard of <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus</hi> formerly, the deſcription <hi>Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi> now gave me of him, could not chooſe but ſurpriſe me. I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways heard him repreſented as the true model of an honeſt man: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving read his Life in Latine, French and Engliſh, I was fully confirm'd in this opinion, and I freely confeſs, I fear'd there might be ſome affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſingularity in your friends ſentiment; he judg'd of my thoughts by my countenance, and having freely own'd it to him, he continu'd his Diſcourſe as follows.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:109194:66"/>
            <p>It is very true, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Perſons, and that are beſt skill'd in theſe matters, are of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry different judgement from me touching the man we ſpeak of, and do not wonder at it. He deceiv'd wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than they, and thoſe that had opportunity of knowing him better. I ſpeak of the learned age wherein he liv'd, wherein I told you already, that his Reputation was as great as I believe it was undeſerved. You muſt not imagine that he was the only perſon of this kind: I'le in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in others both Ancient and Modern when you pleaſe, and 'tis very probable his Hiſtorian took the voice of the People for it, which is not always the voice of God. But his error is no authority, and the character of his <hi>Hero</hi> is of that importance to be clear'd up, that it deſerves to be examin'd a little nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower than he has done it.</p>
            <p>You may gueſs how eaſily Fame is acquir'd by having great Riches, when one knows ever ſo little how to uſe them; to judge aright of a
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109194:66"/>man he ſhould be conſider'd by the qualities which are leaſt ſeen; and there is no degree of Reputation but may be attain'd without virtue; by riches, wit and a great deal of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; there can nothing more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary be taught Gentlemen of your age, than to diſtinguiſh counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit vertues from real, and not to be deceived by common report in the merit of particular perſons. You cannot imagine the trouble one has all their life, for admiring perſons in their youth, which deſerve not to be admired. And when I ſpeak of merit, pray obſerve, that I thereby mean true integrity and honeſty, without which I know not any, and it is that merit which I deny to <hi>Atticus,</hi> for (this excepted) it was hard to have more wit and prudence than he had, or to underſtand the Times, Men and Buſineſs better than he did.</p>
            <p>If what you ſay be true, <hi>reply'd I</hi> to this Diſcourſe, his Hiſtorian is the greateſt flatterer that ever was. Say rather that he was his Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:109194:67"/>ſaid <hi>Caeſarion; Nepos</hi> is in moſt things a down right Lyar, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be but of a mean capacity, as may be judg'd by what we have remaining of his; he took for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant all that his <hi>Hero</hi> ſaid to make himſelf be cry'd up; and relates, as undoubted truth, all that he had heard ſpoken in favour of <hi>Atticus,</hi> by <hi>Atticus</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>One cannot be juſtly more ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than <hi>Nepos</hi> is: he boaſts to have lived ſo familiarly with this Gallant, that he was privy to his Journal of Expences; he interven'd in his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and at his requeſt regiſtr'd ſome of them. It do's not appear that this Hiſtorian made any great Figure in the World, as moſt of his time did; ſo that there's juſt cauſe to ſuſpect, that <hi>Atticus</hi> his friendſhip being the higheſt of his preferment, his own private intereſt moved him to advance the glory of <hi>Atticus</hi> to the higheſt pitch he could. But you ſhall find afterwards that he was ſo unfortunate or indiſcreet, that the moſt glorious actions related by him,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109194:67"/>are either convinc'd of falſhood by other Writers, of greater credit than him, or related in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by himſelf, that unawares he deſtroyes all their Merit in diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their true Original.</p>
            <p>You promiſe me things that are very curious, <hi>reply'd I</hi> to <hi>Caeſarion;</hi> I very much queſtion if any beſides your ſelf could perform your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and you will do me a ſingular pleaſure if you diſcharge it faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. There's no need of being a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry able man, reply'd he, to ſatisfie you therein, and I'le not defer your deſire any longer.</p>
            <p>To render the Oeconomy and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality of <hi>Atticus</hi> the more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to ſhew that he had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd his wealth but by honeſt ways; <hi>Nepos</hi> boldly affirms,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nullius rei neque praes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps. Tu ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanus pendis.</hi> l. 2. ep. 15.</note> that he was never concern'd in buſineſs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly nor indirectly, as other Knights of <hi>Rome</hi> uſually were. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs the quite contrary appears by <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Letters, which <hi>Nepos</hi> himſelf teſtifies to have ſeen; in which this Orator calls <hi>Atticus</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:109194:68"/>in expreſs terms, and gives him an account of a Decree of the <hi>Senate</hi> againſt the Creditors of the Free People, wherein <hi>Atticus</hi> himſelf was concern'd, becauſe he had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd great Sums of mony for thoſe of <hi>Sicionia,</hi> which were of that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>And it would be very ſtrange to conceive, how he ſhould acquire ſuch extraordinary great Riches, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting ſo Liberally, and living ſo Honourably as he did, having never born any Office nor Command, if he had not gained Wealth ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way; and there's no doubt but it was the cauſe that made a learn'd <hi>French Critick,</hi> in ſome obſcure words which he wrote to <hi>Cicero,</hi> diſcover, that he held a Bank at <hi>Rome</hi> in his own Houſe, under the Name of <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi>'s, which were at his Devotion, and made publick profeſſion of it. But I excuſe <hi>Nepos</hi> for being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the thing, for by the dark Enigmatical manner that <hi>Atticus</hi> mentions it to <hi>Cicero,</hi> it may eaſily be ſeen that he conceal'd it with
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:109194:68"/>extraordinary care, and made not his Hiſtorian privy to it.</p>
            <p>In another place to exaggerate the great eſteem every body had for him; the ſame Hiſtorian poſitively affirms, that <hi>Pompey</hi> had no ill will for him, for ſtaying in <hi>Italy</hi> during the Civil Wars, without joyning to any ſide, although he was bound in ſtrict bands of Amity to this great Man. Nevertheleſs the ſame <hi>Cicero,</hi> who muſt needs know things better than <hi>Nepos,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam eſſe illius vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctcriae. Veſtrum plane di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim de te ipſo niſi crudeliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum eſt.</hi> ep. 6. l. 11.</note> ſeeing he was at that time with <hi>Pompey</hi> in <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> writes in expreſs terms to <hi>Atticus</hi> after the Death of this General, that he eſteem'd them equally his Enemies, that had not follow'd and ſided with him, I ſay you as well as others, <hi>ſays Cicero, for it was determin'd, to have us'd you Cruelly, if we had return'd to</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>I would inſtance in ſundry other places, wherein <hi>Nepos</hi> has not been more faithful, than in theſe two now mention'd, but as that would be too tedious, ſo I'le content my ſelf to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one more, after which, you
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:109194:69"/>will the eaſier credit the reſt; it is where he affirms,
<note place="margin">Ciceroni in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ejus periculis ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem fidem praebuit.</note> that <hi>Atticus had a perfect kindneſs for Cicero in all his troubles.</hi> You ſhall heare what <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf ſaith, and I cannot ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently admire the impudence of this Writer, to dare affirm a thing ſo boldly, in a Work wherein he ſpeaks in the praiſe of Letters writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf to his <hi>Hero;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">L 3. ep. 15.24. &amp;c.</note> whereas the very ſame Letters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch the quite contrary, and are full of reproofs and juſt and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment complaints, which <hi>Cicero</hi> makes of <hi>Atticus,</hi> to <hi>Atticus</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>I am not any longer ſurpris'd at <hi>Nepos</hi>'s Errours, <hi>ſaid I</hi> to <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> by what you have related to me of him. But I much admire at <hi>Atticus,</hi> by what you have now ſaid, and I could never have thought, but that ſo great a Friendſhip, as that betwixt him and <hi>Cicero,</hi> ſhould have been maintain'd on both parts with all the fidelity imaginable; you won't ſo much wonder at it, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> if you conſider what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low's, with a little more heed than
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:109194:69"/>you have hitherto done. You will not find in him any ſymptom of true goodneſs, and it cannot be ſaid it was the commerce of the World that deprav'd him, becauſe in this reſpect he was the ſame in his Youth as he was in his riper Years.</p>
            <p>His Father dyed when he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Young, and left him Wealth more than enough to ſerve him as long as he liv'd. For his Quality, he was but of the Equeſtrian Order, that is to ſay, a good Alderman or Citizen. In his Youth when the moſt timorous have ſome courage, he quited <hi>Italy,</hi> and retir'd to <hi>Athens</hi> under a pretence of ſtudying, but in effect, it was becauſe a Seditious <hi>Tribune</hi> had been executed at <hi>Rome,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anicia Pompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brina nupſerat</hi> M. <hi>Servio fratri</hi> P. <hi>Sulpitii qui tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus plebis interfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt.</hi>
               </note> whoſe Brother had Marry'd <hi>Atticus</hi> his Couſin-german, this was, as you may perceive, to ſee a ſtorm far off; and one could not have deſir'd more favourable circumſtances of becoming a perfect Epicure than theſe were, as he verifi'd afterwards. I don't de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to cenſure this Sect, I perfectly know it's ſentiments as well as you:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:109194:70"/>Nevertheleſs I cannot but ſay, that 'tis a ſtrange kind of Wiſdom, to ſee ones Country on the point of utter ruin, without concerning ones ſelf one way or other, although one has Extraordinary means and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſerving it; and to ſuffer all things to be turn'd upſide-downe, rather than to be expos'd to the leaſt danger. I make no doubt, but you have heard of the Law of <hi>Solon,</hi> that declar'd thoſe Infamous, which took not ſome ſide or other in a publick Inſurrection. But this Subject would ingage us too far; you may only obſerve, that this kind of temper of profound indifferency, not to ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibleneſs, which <hi>Atticus</hi> had all his life, for all things which did not directly concern himſelf, was the true cauſe of his continual proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and it was this proſperity that made him cheifly to be admir'd. But it is an eaſie matter to be happy when one is left rich, enjoys wit and health, and cares for no body.</p>
            <p>Do you call that, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> caring for no body, to ſupport ones Friends,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:109194:70"/>when they are forſaken by all the World, with money and all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in their need, without expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any return or recompence: Yes <hi>anſwer'd Caeſarion</hi> unconcernedly; I call this proceeding, vanity, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, policy, in fine, any thing rather than true Liberality, when it is ſo diſſembled, artifitial, and ſelf-ended, as was that of <hi>Atticus,</hi> when it has only vain glory for it's ſcope, and do's not appear as well in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate as on publick occaſions.</p>
            <p>He ſent money to young <hi>Marius</hi> his ſchoolfellow, when he fled pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcib'd by <hi>Sylla;</hi> it was the greateſt name of <hi>Rome,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Neque longius quam dictum eſſet cos debere paſſus fit, neque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgendo inveter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſcere eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum as altenum patieba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> and it was hard to judge at that time, if he would not become more powerful than ever he was before, according to what had lately hapn'd his Father. He lent to the <hi>Athenians</hi> conſiderable ſums of Money without Intreſt, to pay their City Debts, and <hi>Nepos</hi> commends him, <hi>for requiring it to be paid punctually at the prefixt time;</hi> ſo great an itch had he to praiſe him on any ſcore. He could not better have beſtow'd his
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:109194:71"/>Liberality than upon the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious City in the World, which he had choſe for the place of his retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at a time when he thought it not overſafe to ſtay at <hi>Rome.</hi> And all kind of reſpects were pay'd him in acknowledgement thereof, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was done but by his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Advice; it proceeded ſo far, that they erected Statues in his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whether he would or no, in the moſt publick places in the City.</p>
            <p>I ſee nothing, ſaid I, but what was very commendable in this action; the <hi>Athenians</hi> gratitude could not render the thing to be done out of ſelf-intereſt, and it ſeems to me to inhance the kindneſs, rather than to leſſen it. If there be no more in't than to ſay <hi>Atticus</hi> did it through vain glory; then the beſt and moſt commendable actions may by the ſame reaſon be ſenſur'd, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing may be eſteem'd vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious when
'tis known, that is, as ſoon as it comes to be ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, reply'd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> he did more generous actions than
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:109194:71"/>theſe were in appearance, the which however <hi>Cicero</hi> did not very well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of; and after the manner that he dealt with <hi>Atticus,</hi> it may ſafely be affirm'd, that he put no great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue on theſe ſplendid Liberalities, ſeeing he cannot forbear writing ſlightly of them unto <hi>Atticus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he in a certain place, <note place="margin">Sed heus tu Ache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet hoc tibi.</note> 
               <hi>Is it true that you have diſtributed Corn to the</hi> Athenians, <hi>do you think it's well done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe, if I miſtake not, intimates that theſe actions were at leaſt much ſuſpected in thoſe times, when they could be better judg'd of than now; and <hi>Cicero</hi>'s authority is of far greater weight in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than that of <hi>Nepos.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it muſt be granted, it would be unjuſt to ſenſure them, did one know no more than what this Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian do's relate; but he reporting others of the ſame ſtamp, which are undoubtly falſe, one may by the ſame meaſure the more naturally judge of thoſe that be dubious.</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:109194:72"/>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Caeſar</hi> it was propos'd amongſt the Roman Knights, to raiſe a ſtock for the maintenance of his Aſſaſſinates, in conſideration of the pretended ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they had done the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. One of theſe Knights who had the chief conduct of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thinking he could not better advance it, than by ingaging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one of the chief of his Order, addreſs'd himſelf unto <hi>Atticus,</hi> as unto a particular friend of <hi>Brutus,</hi> who was chief of the Murderers. What anſwer think you <hi>Atticus</hi> made unto this propoſal? <note place="margin">Ille con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſionis globus hujus u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſione diſſectus eſt qui officia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micis praeſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſine factione exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maret, &amp;c.</note> there was need of maintaining an action, which at that time was eſteemed generous by every body, and there appear'd no danger in doing it. <hi>He made the whole deſign fall to the ground</hi> (ſaith <hi>Nepos</hi>) <hi>thinking it not fit to ſerve his friends by a ſpirit of faction.</hi> Did you ever ſee a poorer excuſe, nor the word Faction worſe apply'd? and that you may the plainer ſee that he refus'd only out of ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Affairs having quite chang'd
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:109194:72"/>ſoon after, and <hi>Brutus</hi> with his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices being forc'd to withdraw, <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus</hi> ſent him conſiderable ſums of mony of free gift. But who doth not ſee that this ſupply, how great ſoever, could not be comparable to that which was deſign'd to be given him by the greateſt part of the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyeſt Citizens, of which he was depriv'd by <hi>Atticus</hi> his refuſal: and to conclude, this denial could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed only from an affectation of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtinguiſh'd from all others, without any other end or aim, but an envious fear and jealouſie of ſharing with his equals in the glory of a good action.</p>
            <p>It's true, reply'd I, there appears ſomething very ſtrange in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and that renders it ſomething ſuſpitious, and I cannot but own it. But in requital you muſt grant in the next place, that there could be nothing more free and generous, than what he did a while after in regard of <hi>Antonius.</hi> One had need be ſomthing more than a Prophet, to foreſee the <hi>Triumvirat</hi> during the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:109194:73"/>Seige of <hi>Modena; Antonius</hi> declar'd an Enemy by the <hi>Senate,</hi> routed, and fors'd to raiſe the Seige by <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> and the <hi>Conſuls,</hi> his whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my diſpers'd and ſlain, himſelf flying into <hi>Gaul</hi> to the mercy of <hi>Lepiddus,</hi> abandon'd by his beſt Friends, and perſecuted by ſome of them as by his worſt Enemies; his Wife and Children expos'd every moment to the greateſt Extremitys. In this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable condition <hi>Atticus</hi> entertains and ſupports thoſe of his, that held true to him, ſupply's them with all neceſſaries; accompanies <hi>Fulvia</hi> in all places, interceeds for her, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes her caution, lends her mony without intreſt, to pay Debts which were falen due, without obliging her to repayment. It ſeems to me that 'tis not enough to be good and diſintereſted to act after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but alſo it ſhews reſoluteneſs and great courage.</p>
            <p>To anſwer the exaggeration you have now made, reply'd <hi>Caeſarion;</hi> before we examine this matter to the bottom, let me deſire you to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:109194:73"/>make? reflection, which I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from a good authority, which perhaps you have never yet thought of. At theſe words <hi>Caeſarion</hi> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing about what he intended to ſay, we heard a noiſe of ſeveral Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Court, which obliged us to riſe and ſee what it meant.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Third Day.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:109194:74"/>
            <head>CAESARION. The <hi>Fourth</hi> Day.</head>
            <p>OUr Converſation was deferr'd for ſome time by company that came to viſit your friend, and though it wrought in me ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions not very agreeable unto one of my years, yet I can ſay without vanity, that it was with great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction I return'd unto it. Beſides the extraordinary deſire one has na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to improve ones ſelf in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, having never met a man that condeſcended more to humour my weak apprehenſion; our diſcourſe had alſo in it the pleaſure of Novelty, and I was ſenſibly taken in that part that was moſt grateful to me. I fanci'd therefore to be return'd to the light after a long darkneſs, the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:109194:74"/>firſt time we met together alone, and the delight I conceived might have been diſcern'd in my looks by any body elſe, as well as by him. It was, I ſhall never forget it, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry afternoon of the ſame day that our Company went away, we walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame Gallery talking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, which I told you fac'd his Cloſet; and as he could not but wonder at the pleaſure I took in his diſcourſe, not knowing otherwiſe how to divert the commendations he gave me on that account, and which was burdenſome to me; I bethought my ſelf of asking him the meaning of the firſt Picture that offer'd it ſelf to my view, amongſt ſeveral others that were in the ſame place.</p>
            <p>It repreſented a Man with a Face as great as it was ill fetur'd, very ill accouter'd after the Greek habit, leaning with one Hand upon his Staff, and ſtretching out the other, half open, unto a Statue richly adorn'd. Nere this man lay an empty Veſſel, part of the Head being out, the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:109194:75"/>bottom of the Cask might be ſeen: without much difficulty, by this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipage I knew it was the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Diogenes,</hi> but the poſture where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was repreſented appearing ſomething ſtrange, I deſir'd to know of <hi>Caeſarion</hi> what it ſignifi'd; I'le make you, reply'd he, the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>Paulus Emilius</hi> made thoſe that deſir'd him in the behalf of King <hi>Perſeus</hi> his priſoner, that he might not be carri'd in Tryumph through <hi>Rome, That he would ask it of his own ſelf.</hi> If I underſtood what the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had done, ſaid I, I ſhould not have any need to ask the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it of my ſelf, nor of you. And have you not heard, reply'd he, that ſometimes one knows things that one thinks they be ignorant of. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire therefore of your own ſelf with a little reflection, what this poſture means, and you will find at laſt, that you will reſolve your own ſelf as well as I can.</p>
            <p>This Picture, ſaid he, is not like moſt others which repreſent Hiſtories. Painters have not alwayes the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:109194:75"/>as good as the ſight, they think that all things are alike fit to be painted, yet there be but few things proper to be painted, for the Penſill not being capable, to give the Figures motion upon the Cloth, it cannot repreſent but very imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe Objects which conſiſt in motion, as Combats, bodily Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Tempeſts, Incendiaries, and moſt of thoſe things which they moſt of all delight in. I know not if any body elſe has felt the diſpleaſure that I have done, in conſidering this kind of Painting, for methinks the Figures ought to have Motion, and the Moving Poſture wherein they be repreſented, though in effect they are immovable, doth imply a kind of contradiction, wherewith my mind is ſomewhat diſſatisfi'd.</p>
            <p>At this rate, ſaid I, you had need of Comedians or Stage-players to repreſent things, and you would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive Painters of the greateſt and pleaſanteſt part of their Profeſſion: That is not my deſign, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> and if it were, I would not venture to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:109194:76"/>it. But I ſay to judge naturally of things, it were better to Paint Hiſtories, whoſe eſſential part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in a fix'd poſture, which the Penſil may very well perform, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there has been ſome inſtances, wherein the perſons concern'd have been in all liklyhood immovable. As for Example, the action of <hi>Saevola,</hi> immovably conſtant holding his hand in the Flames, whil'ſt <hi>Porſenna</hi> and the reſt that beheld him were immovable through admiration. Such alſo was the judgment of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> where the true Mother held the Arm of him that went to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide her Child, whilſt the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mother ſtood immovable in her Obſtinacy. And ſuch to conclude, is the Picture that you ſee. Imagin then what ſenſe you would give the Action it repreſents, if you ſee it in the Original, ſeeing it would be but the ſame that 'tis in the Coppy.</p>
            <p>If paſſing through the <hi>Caemariqae</hi> amongſt the Statues of the Demy Gods of <hi>Greece,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plutar. of Shame.</note> you ſhould ſee <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> proſtrate before one of thoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:109194:76"/>holding out his hand asking an Alms, what would you think of it? I ſhould be much ſtartl'd at it, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> to ſee ſo careleſs a Man begging, and ſo wiſe a Man to begg of a Statue; that is the very reaſon, <hi>riply'd Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> which ſhould make you gueſs the meaning of his poſture. It don't ſeem ſtrange to you to begg of a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but becauſe it cannot give any thing. If then any body asks of it, 'tis not becauſe they think to receive any thing; this demand therefore is not out of Intreſt, it is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore incompatable with the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> there only remaines to inquire why he amus'd himſelf about ſo frivolous (not to ſay ſo fooliſh) an Action.</p>
            <p>To underſtand the true Reaſon, you need only conſider him with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion in this poſture; I ſhould ſoon be try'd, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> and could not long hold out without growing impatient. Admire then, <hi>reply'd Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarion,</hi> the patience of this <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſopher</hi> in ſo unpleaſant an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rciſe, that you cannot behold him
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:109194:77"/>a moment without diſpleaſure. If your Patience cannot reſiſt ſo little a thing, what would you do at <hi>Court,</hi> where you would find a Thouſand greater occaſions to try it. It would be in vain to flatter ones ſelf with Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, If one did not practiſe this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Virtue, as you ſee <hi>Diogenes</hi> here doth. If one do's not beg as he doth without hope of being heard, and of being refus'd too without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourag'd. Importunity perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, boldneſs, theſe be the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities neceſſary to make our ſerviſe acceptable to thoſe Idols, to whom our ambition and covetouſneſs do's ſacrifice the beſt of our daies; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever has theſe qualities, ſhall be heard ſooner or later; without them, wiſdom, valour, goodneſs and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, are but frivolous ornaments.</p>
            <p>You are ſurpris'd at this Diſcourſe, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> ſeeing me ſilent, you thought till now, that Merit alone had been ſufficient to advance a man in the World. The ſeveral Maſters and Tutours you have been under, have only labour'd in a manner to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:109194:77"/>no other end, than to imprint this in your mind: That a perfectneſs in corporal exerciſes and virtuous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities were a neceſſary and infallible means of making a fortune in the World. This is true in one ſenſe; this perſwaſion was neceſſary for you at that time and age, doubtleſs it contributed very much towards your accompliſhment, and it was not very requiſite you ſhould know any more at that time.</p>
            <p>But when you left thoſe Maſters to enter into the commerce of the world, had they fully diſcharg'd themſelves of their duty, they ought to have told you quite another thing, they ought to have told you what you dream't not of, that the beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities both acquir'd and natural, are things difficult to be us'd; that they muſt be conceal'd almoſt as often as ſhewn; that oftentimes they make thoſe conceited that enjoy them, make them ſilly and hated, and ſometimes render them ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and therefore for the moſt part do more hurt than good. That at
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:109194:78"/>beſt they only procure a forc't and unprofitable eſteem, that they have very little contributed unto the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt fortunes that have been made, and that if any that are endow'd with theſe qualities and know beſt to uſe them, arrive at any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary promotion, they ſerv'd only for ſhew, he owes the true cauſe of it to ſome other quality of more value in the main, and which lyes more hid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſarion</hi> ſtoping at theſe words, I confeſs ſaid I, you ſurprize me. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd indeed there was ill ways of advancement, but I alſo concluded that there were good ways no leſs certain, and that a man of good merit might attain good fortune without doing any thing unworthy of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>You are very much deceiv'd, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> a man of this ſtamp is a kind of publick Enemy, which all the world has reaſon to hate; he ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranizes over men by a kind of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, he impoſes upon them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem him; he is the cauſe that all other things are not admir'd as much
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:109194:78"/>as himſelf; he engroſſes a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny applauſes which would ſerve to gratifie a great many others; how then can he but be envy'd?</p>
            <p>This perſwaſion is as firmly root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the minds of men, as the love of glory it ſelf; and it never appear'd more than amongſt the people that were moſt of all enflam'd with a love of this glory. You know againſt what ſort of men the <hi>Oſtraciſm</hi> was ſet up at <hi>Athens:</hi> and doubtleſs you have heard of that Country Fellow that gave his voice for baniſhing <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtides;</hi> he could give no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, but that it diſpleas'd him to hear him always be call'd the <hi>Juſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo de nobis u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat; ſed ſiquis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titerit, alio in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud alios ſit.</hi> Sic. Tuſc. quaeſt. l. 5.</note> So thoſe of <hi>Epheſus</hi> expell'd the moſt virtuous of their Citizens without any other reaſon, but for theſe memorable words, <hi>That none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them ſhould excel above his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and if there be any here that would, let them go excel elſewhere.</hi> So the <hi>Ephori</hi> condemn'd <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> into a Mulct, becauſe he alone poſſeſſed the hearts of the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi> And he that conquer'd <hi>Hanibal</hi> thought he
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:109194:79"/>ought to baniſh himſelf from <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſo he might give liberty to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues inferior to his, to appear there; ſo true it is, that at all times nothing has been more dangerous amongſt men, than too ſhining a merit.</p>
            <p>If this remarkable truth has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in the moſt virtuous and beſt govern'd Common-wealths, do you think it will not appear in Courts, where many times there is neither order nor virtue? There's nothing harder than for ſuch a man as you mean, there to find favour or prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; becauſe thoſe which have the chief power, are not always of ſuch merit, as not to fear ſuch as are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd with higher merit than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. One had need have a great ſtock of virtue, to love it in another as much as it deſerves; this is the moſt aſſured ſign of true merit, and one may, without vanity, be fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of his own, when one does right to that of other mens; that one takes pleaſure in making it known, and that one honours the party indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, in all places, and at all times.</p>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:109194:79"/>
            <p>And ſuch a one was <hi>Scipio,</hi> that I before mention'd to you; and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not better repreſent him to you by this great Idea, than in the very words of his incomparable Hiſtorian. After the unfortunate death of his Father and Unkle in <hi>Spain,</hi> one of their Lieutenants, called <hi>Martius,</hi> maintain'd the glory of <hi>Rome,</hi> which had been ſhrewdly ſhaken by ſuch two terrible blows, that ſcarce any that ſucceeded thoſe two great men, could not well have ſupply'd their place better than him: So that of thoſe that were in <hi>Rome</hi> capable of ſuch imployments, there was none that durſt aſpire to that, in <hi>Spain,</hi> but the Heir of the Illuſtrious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceas'd; he was aged about 24 years. How do you think he carry'd himſelf towards this brave Lieutenant, who would have darkn'd the glory of any other Captain but this, when he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd in his Province? He did not ſet about changing the Orders <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> had given; he did not narrowly ſearch into the faults that might be committed before his coming, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:109194:80"/>ſo many great tranſactions, and of what might have been done better than was done: He kept not ſtrictly his diſtance and port, as was due to him as General, and affected not the reſpect due to it, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Martium ſecum tanto cum honore habeb at, ut facile appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, eum nihil mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, quam ne quis obſtaret gloriae ſuae.</hi> l. 26. Aelian. Hiſt. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. l. 12. c. 16. Quint. Curt. l. 8</note> with this great Perſon, more than he did with others his inferiors: neither did he uſe indirect ways, as moſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders do, to diſparage the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their Predeceſſors; <hi>He had</hi> Martius <hi>always near him,</hi> ſaith Tit. Livius, <hi>and he did him ſo great honour, that 'twas plainly ſeen, he feared not that any body could hinder the progreſs of his glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſurnam'd the Great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd not ſuch a pitch of virtue; he was not ſo ingenious, ſaith the moſt impartial of his Hiſtorians, in valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the virtue and courage of his own Countrymen, as much as he did that of ſtrangers. Another Author makes a long narrative of the good qualities peculiar unto each of his Captains, for which he hated them without any other cauſe, and therefore <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menion,</hi> him that of all others knew
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:109194:80"/>him beſt, ſaid for an only leſſon to <hi>Philotas, My Son be little in thine own eſteem.</hi> If a perſon of ſo eminent degree as this Conqueror, was not free from jealouſie, how can it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that the moſt part of the great Men, we ſpeak of, can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from it? And what aſſiſtance can a man of true virtue and merit hope from ſuch, in prefering him at Court? Yet what poſſibility is there of being conſider'd without the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable recommendation of ſome or other? The Princes favour and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will is already ingag'd, how virtuous and valiant ſoever a perſon is, he muſt not think to be regarded for that reaſon alone, unleſs he is ingag'd to do it by ſome other way and means. It's poſſible he may do you right, ſhould he reward your merits; but how unlikely is it, that he will trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf to inquire into your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts? Something elſe is requiſite for the attaining your ends.</p>
            <p>A Prince that has already choſe and ſetled his affection upon his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Favourites, before ever
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:109194:81"/>you were thought of, thinks that he has no further need of any body elſe; he ſees by their Eyes, hears by their Ears, and for the moſt part Judges by their judgement: So that any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that offer their ſervice, otherwiſe than by their means, is not regarded by him, he muſt move out of his Sphere to do otherwiſe: being only familiarly acquainted with them, he knows not if there be any others that excel them; and herein he reſembles that Woman amongſt the Ancients, that ſuppos'd all men had ſtinking breath, becauſe ſhe never kiſs'd any but her own Husband.</p>
            <p>Moreover, Favourites and great Miniſters, looking upon the Princes favour to be uncertain, and a thing that may be loſt; they dread nothing more than a man that is endow'd with the many good qualities you ſpeak of; they knowing him a long time, do judge better than new Comers the effects it may produce in the mind of their Maſter; they know how to repreſent ſuch of theſe qualities as may not be pleaſing, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:109194:81"/>uſe all means to hinder thoſe from being known, which would pleaſe too much.</p>
            <p>And do not imagine, that 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt alone that makes them act in this manner, in diſſipating the cloud that threatens them, it is the general practice of Courtiers to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed this way, although they drive at ſeveral ends; and the moſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite agree in this, to diſcourage por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of extraordinary merit from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any ſhear in the Prince his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, although they cannot but have a great eſteem for ſuch themſelves. It is a compact which they be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclin'd to, and they never fail to agree in the executing of it: they have no need of conſulting, nor of being advis'd to joyn together in theſe occaſions; envy and vanity, wherewith they are equally poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd, directs them to the ſame end, more than all the conſultatious in the World can do.</p>
            <p>Let but one of them begin to tell a ridiculous ſtory of ſuch a Perſon as this, either falſe, or ſo groſly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:109194:82"/>that it can ſcarſe be diſcerned by thoſe which know the contrary; he is ſurpris'd, that another, who it may be know's not ſo much as he do's, ſhould preſently give ſuch cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what he heard, that the other might be ready, to gueſs at what he ſo cunningly invented. Two or three ſuch ill Offices as this, were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ruin any Man, were he never ſo well eſteem'd by his <hi>Prince,</hi> who if not very wiſe, never inquires into the Cauſe of things; or if he doth, is not for the moſt part more favourable to Perſons of extraordinary Merit, than his Courtiers are.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is, that he ſcarce ever regards ſuch Perſons as theſe be, for Men are ſtartl'd at the leaſt inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he has for them, and then they are envi'd by all the World; and this general deſign of ruining them, which is a neceſſary Conſequence of the goodneſs of his choiſe, diſcourages the <hi>Prince</hi> and naturally inclines him to be ſuſpitious.</p>
            <p>It may plainly be perceiv'd, that the general averſion he find's in
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:109194:82"/>Mens minds for the good choice he ſhould make, do's at length reduce him to the neceſſity of making a bad one, and then he finds no longer any oppoſition; for it is only Virtue and Merit which are ſuſpected; a Man is ſeldom hated for being Vitious, the firſt favours beſtow'd on him are not ſuſpected, they are attributed to ſome other Cauſe, and
'tis not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they can hold long, yet ſuch a perſon eaſily and without oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by his corruptneſs, Eſtabliſhes himſelf in the <hi>Princes</hi> favour, to the Admiration of all the World; It is not believ'd till 'tis too late, and the wiſdom of the <hi>Prince</hi> being ingag'd, he is bound in honour to vindicate it, and will not be perſwaded to the contrary of what he has done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſarion</hi> having deliver'd this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with ſome concerndneſs, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at theſe words, I could not but teſtify to him my Aſtoniſhment at what he ſaid; for although the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence ſeem'd very natural in hearing him, yet I did not well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to what it tended. If it be ſo,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:109194:83"/>
               <hi>ſaid I,</hi> nothing is more difficult, than for a <hi>Prince</hi> to make a wiſe choice; there's no queſtion of it, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> for he never underſtands the perſons that he chooſes, and all that are about him agree to couſen him; and the life of thoſe eſpecially that are neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt him is nothing elſe but a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Fars,</hi> wherein all things are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him in Maſquerade: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever methinks, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> when it falls out that he makes any extraordinary ill choiſe, it being the intreſt of a great many to inform him of it, it cannot chooſe, but in time he muſt be ſomwhat ſenſible of it, and ſo by conſequence reform his errour. Then you think it a ſmall matter, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> to confeſs that one is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aken; this averſion being natural to all Men, is more particularly rooted in the ſpirits of <hi>Princes.</hi> Vain glory is ſo inherent to them, that 'twere almoſt unjuſt to cenſure them for it. Pray tell me which is the beſt courſe they can take in the condition you place them, either to publiſh to the World the ill choiſe they have made
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:109194:83"/>by correcting it; or by continuing to perſiſt in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now by this demand I underſtand your meaning. I find that what you ſay of <hi>Favorites</hi> is true, and that a <hi>Prince</hi> is much in the right, not to change them how bad ſoever they be. But methinks it ſhould not be ſo of his Miniſters; no certainly, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> Favorites are not directly concern'd with publick affairs, all their actions do only regard the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and particular actions of the <hi>Prince;</hi> ſo that the little Merit they have, is ſcarce known to any, but to thoſe which be as near the <hi>Prince</hi> as themſelves, and ſuch are ſufficiently concern'd not to diſcloſe it to the reſt of the World.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, the Function of Miniſters of State being publick, a <hi>Prince</hi> that has made an ill choiſe of them cannot hide the Errour he has committed in perſevering in it; and rather than convince the World of their incapacity, one of theſe two things is believ'd; either that he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it not, and that ignorant
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:109194:84"/>as they be, he thinks them very able, becauſe they are wiſer than him, or that, if he wants not judgment, and is deſtitute of humanity and true glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſeeing he cares not that all the World ſhould ſuffer through his Fault, and is leſs ſenſible of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples juſt grievance, than at the ſhame of owning his own Errour.</p>
            <p>And is it not juſt, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> at theſe words, to judge after this ſort? One cannot judge otherwiſe, <hi>anſwer'd Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarion,</hi> but <hi>Princes</hi> do not think ſo. And what can they think, when they prefer perſons to the greateſt Imployments, that are not capable of diſcharging the leaſt? They think, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> and they are not altogeather deceiv'd, that moſt Men do not judge of things themſelves, and much leſs of thoſe things that are above their Capacity: that 'tis eaſie to deceive the ſight, when one appears but ſeldom and at a diſtance; to hide ones Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance when one ſpeaks but ſeldom, or when one liſts, and when one is not bound to be accountable for on's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. To give an outward attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:109194:84"/>and ſeemingly liſten to Diſcourſe, and yet though they did ſo ſeriouſly, do not at all comprehend what they hear. To conclude, they believe that the number of thoſe that have judgment ſufficient, to diſtinguiſh truth through the miſt of errour, and have courage to defend it, being but very few in compariſon of the contrary party, their wiſdom and freedom makes them only be ſcoffed at, and they be ſuppreſs'd by the great numbers of thoſe who are not ſo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, or if they be, dare not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what they think.</p>
            <p>But grant that all this were true, <hi>ſaid I</hi> again, were it not better and more glorious for a <hi>Prince,</hi> to chooſe Miniſters, that ſtood not in need of theſe poor ſhifts, to conceal their little Merit from the ſight of the World? There's no doubt of it, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> but you don't conſider, that moſt great Men deſire not to be often ſeen, nor narrowly diſcern'd by Men of great Virtue and Merit.</p>
            <p>Perſons do not make choiſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Men, any farther than
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:109194:85"/>they reſemble them. It is only a wiſe <hi>Prince,</hi> that will make choiſe of a wiſe Miniſter, and that will praiſe him, and declare to the World the benefit he receives thereby. Let us drink ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> making a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch amongſt his Friends, in the midſt of his greateſt affairs, <hi>Let us Drink,
<note place="margin">Athen. l. 10.</note> it is ſufficient that</hi> Antipater <hi>is ſober.</hi> This in my opinion, is the higheſt commendation that ever was given by a Sovereign to a ſubject. To ſpeak after this manner, <hi>Philip</hi> muſt needs look upon the great Merit of <hi>Antipater,</hi> as making up a part of his own. A <hi>Prince</hi> that gave ſo high an Encomium to his Miniſter, had no cauſe to be jealous of him; he muſt be as excellent a <hi>Prince,</hi> as his Miniſter was an excellent Miniſter. And had I no other proof than this Diſcourſe, I ſhould be no leſs aſſur'd of it, than by the great things which daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhews us.</p>
            <p>It's true, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> that of all the paſſages of Antiquity, that I have heard of, none touch'd me ſoſenſibly as this did. Do not you find therein
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:109194:85"/>as well as I, <hi>ſaid Caeſarion,</hi> ſomthing that appears not only natural and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, but alſo noble and great? In the liberty of Wine and feaſting of thoſe Times, which was not ſo regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar as in our Daies, to have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Mind excuſing his exceſs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when it might have been conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at, to thoſe that might have blam'd it, and of giving a ſober ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, although the time and place might have diſpenſed him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whoſoever knew how to make a Debauch in this manner, could not be much prejudic'd thereby.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Diſcourſe; Do not imagin that all great Men, ſuch as the <hi>King</hi> we ſpeak of, do glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in having near them Perſons of the Merit of <hi>Antipater:</hi> An excellent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter cannot ſute with a <hi>Prince</hi> of little judgment; it's enough that he may have good ſervants, and 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo true, that ſuch will never preſerve him from falling into danger. If <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> had been a Man of ſuch a Soul, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> had never been Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the World. Theſe are excellent
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:109194:86"/>Mariners in calm and fair weather, and during a proſperous Gale, but the firſt Storm they ſoon are ſplit to pieces on ſome Rock or Sands. But they have the pleaſure for a while to diceive the World, and to be thought able perſons amongſt ſuch as be not ſo; their very Shipwrack which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakens the moſt inſenſible, do's not alwaies reclaim the <hi>Prince</hi> from his Errour; they impute the misfortune to the Winds or Planets, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he do's not excuſe them, yet had he rather be diſhonour'd by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that he can ſomtimes look upon as inferiour to him, than to be well ſerv'd by others, that he muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to admire.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell, <hi>anſwer'd I,</hi> at theſe words, if there be any ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> as thoſe you ſpeak of; but I know that <hi>Auguſtus</hi> whom you mention'd but now, was none of the number: You may, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> be deceiv'd as well as many others; he had a great deal of witt and ingenuity, 'tis not to be deny'd; but he was not altogeather ſo great a Genius as moſt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:109194:86"/>do imagin, grounding their beleif upon the report of ſome Modern Writers, who have not had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ſufficient to be competent Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in the Caſe. And I am much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, <hi>continu'd he,</hi> if you are not well pleas'd at what I ſhall relate to you of him.</p>
            <p>You know better than I, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abſtinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſu ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum Diu prae pudore, &amp; jam de necan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beravit.</hi> Suet.</note> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inform'd of his Daughters miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, he was at the ſame time ſo afflicted in hearing that it was known, and ſo exaſperated againſt her, for the ſingular circumſtances wherewith it was attended: <hi>That he not only refus'd to appear in in publick for a confiderable time, but had alſo thoughts of putting his Daughter to Death.</hi> But altering his mind, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De ſilia abſens, ac libello per Quaeſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citato ſub notum ſenatui fecit.</hi> ibid.</note> inſtead of wholly conniving at her Debauches, not being willing to puniſh them as they deſerv'd, he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare <hi>complaining to the</hi> Senate, <hi>by a Memorial which he caus'd there to be read publickly to that purpoſe.</hi> It was his Cuſtom after this manner to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part his moſt important Affaires, whether Publick or Domeſtick, to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:109194:87"/>the Fathers of the <hi>Senate,</hi> when he did not do it in perſon. But ſome time after, his anger and grief giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place to his Reaſon, he repented publiſhing his own Shame, in ſuch a manner as all the World was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the buſineſs, and in the juſt diſpleaſure therof cry'd out more than once: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Horum mihi ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet, ſi aut</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa, <hi>aut</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coenas <hi>vixiſſet.</hi> Senec. 6 <hi>de</hi> Benef.</note> 
               <hi>That if</hi> Agrippa <hi>or</hi> Mecae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas <hi>had been alive, he had not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch an Errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing can be more to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject we ſpeak of, than what you have now mention'd. This unfortunate Father, ſo happy in all things elſe, knew very well, as you ſee, the great need that a <hi>Prince</hi> has (be he never ſo able himſelf) of a Miniſter, that may be as able or wiſer than himſelf; of one that he may love and eſteeme ſo much, as to ſuffer him to reclaime him when he doth amiſs. And to quit this old pernitious Maxim of Court; <hi>If thou doſt hinder thy Maſter from Falling, he will not be ſenſible, that 'tis thou that Raiſeſt him up.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive me, there are but very few, that will own, as this <hi>Emperor</hi> did,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:109194:87"/>that their <hi>Counſellours</hi> have more wiſdom than they. And were I to begin the World agine, I ſhould be cautious how I judg'd of others by him; and I would rather give credit to a Courtier belonging to <hi>Emanuel</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> whoſe Example may ſerve for a Rule, to all able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that have to do with great Men.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Prince,</hi> having a Letter of importance to write, commanded one of his Gentlemen to do it; the Gentleman perform'd his part the beſt he could, and carri'd it to the <hi>King:</hi> The <hi>King,</hi> having read it, drew one out of his Pocket, that he had compos'd himſelfe about the ſame buſineſs, and comparing them togeather, he ingeniouſly confeſs'd, that the Gentleman's was the beſt, and that he would make uſe of it. What reflection, think you, made the Courtier on this Diſcourſe; he took no farther notice of it, but making a profound Obeyſance, went preſently and took leave of his beſt Friend, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, <hi>That he had no more to do at</hi>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:109194:88"/>Court, <hi>the</hi> King <hi>knew that he had more witt than himſelf.</hi> I do not conceive, <hi>reply'd I,</hi> at this ſtory, that this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is af any great moment. In all likelihood this Gentleman was too ſoon alarm'd, and the Noble ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Maſter, in doing him juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, would have produc'd other effects, than to expel a perſon of his Merit. As it was more glorious to the <hi>King</hi> to ſubmit, than it was to the Courtier to be ſubmitted to; he had more reaſon to be jealous of his Maſter, than to feare that his Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould be jealous of him, and it could not be thought, but a <hi>Prince,</hi> that could do ſo generous an Action, would alſo put a due value upon it.</p>
            <p>Nothing can be better imagin'd, than what you have now expreſs'd, <hi>reply'd Caeſarion,</hi> to me: Nevertheleſs as nothing oblig'd the <hi>King</hi> to ſhew his Letter, and it not being to his Credit to do it; it may well be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd he did it unawares, and that he repented doing of it. Now if you do not think, that the effects of the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:109194:88"/>diſpleaſure he had for it, would not fall on him, that was the occaſion of it, you have not the ſame Idea of the hearts of Men that I have, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of great Men.</p>
            <p>How can they, without diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, acknowledge themſelves infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, in any thing, to perſons that are ſo far from being worthy to be their Equals? All that they hear or ſee tends only to make them believe that they are above all things; what appearance is there, that they can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſo pleaſant an impreſſion? Men not only endeavour to give them an opinion of the greateſt Idea of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but alſo ſtrive to find high myſteries in the explication they make of the meaneſt of their expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which they could never have dreamt of themſelves, by turning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ridioule the good Qualities of their Equals, thereby to provoke their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and what is worſt of all, and moſt tends to corrupt them, is, by diſguiſing their greateſt faults with the names of virtues which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them.</p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:109194:89"/>
            <p>Now if private perſons, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotelis diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia, poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Rex ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellatus ſit, crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbum, immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum fuiſſe.</hi> Cic. ad Att. l. 13. ep. 2.8</note> whoſe whole life is nothing but a continual paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from one ſubjection to another, or that at leaſt ſpend the greateſt part of it with perſons that have no need to flatter us, find it ſo difficult to rule our paſſions and ſelf-love: how ſhould a great Prince, whoſe ſtate is a kind of continual intoxication, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reaſonable, without it be by a ſpecial grace of God, or by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gift of wiſdom?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do you not ſee,</hi> cry'd the greateſt Wit in <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpeaking familiarly to his beſt friend of what might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> (who then appear'd very moderate) if once he became peaceable and abſolute Maſter of the Commonwealth, <hi>Do you not ſee</hi> (ſaith he unto him) <hi>how the Diſciple of</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle <hi>ſo wiſe, ſo modeſt, became paſſionate, cruel and proud, as ſoon as he was mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As able as he thought himſelf, this great Judge was however deceiv'd in his opinion: the <hi>Roman,</hi> he prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi'd ſo ill of, made as great a progreſs in virtue, even to his death, as the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:109194:89"/>
               <hi>Greek,</hi> to whom he reſembles him, had done in vice. But <hi>Caeſar</hi> had been 50 years a private perſon, and beſides we do not every day find a <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that I will ſay, but that our age has produc'd great Spirits, that do move in high Spheres. Nature is as liberal and vigorous as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; not to inſtance in thoſe whoſe reputation equals their merit, ſuch as the invincible Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> envy'd by the whole World. I was told, ſome years paſt, of a great Prince, who at 13 years of age, being prais'd by his Courtiers, for ſome Action that he was not over well ſatisfi'd withal himſelf, he anſwer'd in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them of their flattery, <hi>I Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi fanno ſempre tutto bene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But once again, ſuch Anſwers are not heard every day; and for my part, very far from wondring or thinking ſtrange, that perſons of this degree ſhould not have the Merit which is duo unto them, I rather think it ſtrange, that they do not reaſon as <hi>Caligula</hi> did, and that our
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:109194:90"/>blind ſubmiſſion to their unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſires ſhould raiſe their Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption unto the higheſt extravagance, <hi>Seeing thoſe that conduct droves of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> (ſaid the fool) <hi>are not beaſts like themſelves, <note place="margin">Philo. in his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſ.</note> but are of a more excellent nature; is it not juſt, that thoſe which command ſo abſolutely over men, and whom all others obey, ſhould be more than men, like thoſe over whom they command?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the effect our flattery do's naturally produce in the Spirit of Princes, and it is what frequently hapn'd for the moſt part in the times of <hi>Papaniſm.</hi> But if our holy Religion do's not allow of theſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theoſes, yet it do's ſo well eſtabliſh the abſolute Authority of Princes, that it is much eaſier for them to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in this regard, than it was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore to thoſe deifi'd Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Caeſarion</hi> had done ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I was ſo concern'd at what he ſaid, that I fancy'd I ſtill heard him; his diſcourſe ſeem'd ſo ſtrange to me, and withal ſo apparent, that I knew
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:109194:90"/>not what judgement to make of it. On one hand I had much difficulty to diſuſe my ſelf from admiring the condition of Princes, whom I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways heard call'd Gods upon earth; on the other hand I could not deny the weakneſs's which he demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they were inclin'd to. But at length, truth carrying a kind of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty with it, which no prejudice is able to reſiſt, I could not avoid being of his judgement; and in this manner, with as great pleaſure as good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, I diveſted my ſelf of the ſtrong opinion I ſuck'd in, in my youth.</p>
            <p>At this rate, reply'd I at length, having paus'd a while, the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Kings is a deplorable ſtate; to judge rightly of it, there's no ſtate more miſerable, ſaid <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> and which deſerves more pity; and it is whereof we ought to be well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded when we go to Court. On the contrary, anſwer'd I, methinks this perſwaſion ſeems to diſcourage us from ingaging at all at Court: you are much miſtaken, ſaid he. A Courtier that looks upon greatneſs
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:109194:91"/>with ſuch an eye, not as a ſovereign Good, but as a Good whoſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences are commonly attended with error and ignorance, will not be ſo eaſily agitated with thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly and furious deſires of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, which trouble the mind in the ſame degree as it excites it, which makes a man take ill mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and inſpires him with raſhneſs and folly. Ambition thruſts him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards barefac'd, it do's not tranſport him beyond himſelf with joy nor grief at the appearance of frowns or ſmiles; it do's not make him, through greedineſs or impatience, guilty of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſe ſtep, which may without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity oblige him to diſcover his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and which may render him ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous if he ſhould not ſucceed in them: There appears nothing but what is decent, equal, and moderate in all his dealings. If he do's not arrive at ſome great fortune by theſe meanes, yet at leaſt he expoſes not himſelf much, and 'tis no diſgrace not to obtain, what he do's not very eagerly purſue.</p>
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:109194:91"/>
            <p>Indeed a man of this temper may be a Courtier all days of his life; he conſiders it as a School, where he muſt go to receive his Maſters directions, and not as an employment. If he ſeeks his Princes favour, it is that he might be ſerviceable to him, either to make Religion flouriſh amongſt his Subjects, or to defend them from their Enemies, or to ſee that they have Juſtice done them. But not to do any thing all his life, but gaze at a man, and to ſeek all occaſions to ſhew himſelf, he would not think all the Riches and Honour in the World worth he getting, by ſuch an idle diſſembling ſort of life.</p>
            <p>Not but that he likes Riches, and approves of Honour and Glory, and will ſpare no juſt means to attain them; it is becauſe he thinks not that true Glory, which is attain'd by theſe ways. It may be offer'd to him at a rate that he thinks unreaſonable; he knows what to lay out before he cheapens it, he will give for it no more than 'tis worth, and if it be ovevalu'd, he will not diſparage it,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:109194:92"/>but thinks he ſhould be counted a fool to buy it at too dear a rate.</p>
            <p>And do not think, that 'tis out of any diſreſpect or averſion for Princes that he is of this opinion, or becauſe he thinks them to be unfortunate and corrupt. The faults, which would deſerve his hatred in private perſons, only excite his pity towards Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and as it is the moſt active of all the Paſſions in a generous ſoul, it inclines him naturally to aſſiſt them, and not to ſhun and abandon them to the mercy of Cheats and Flatterers; he ſatisfies himſelf in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all honeſt ways and means to procure their favour and good liking, that they may ſee the need of having ſuch as him near them: If they were duely inform'd, they would ſpare no coſt of employing ſuch in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for he excuſeth in them a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand things, which thoſe that envy them do condemn: He ſaith, that it would not be only unjuſt, but alſo inhumane to reproach them with defects, which are almoſt inſeparable from their quality; very far from that
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:109194:92"/>dark, black and malitious ſpight, mix'd with indignation and envy, where with moſt of them that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach their perſons be infected; he bears to them the pity and tenderneſs that a Father doth to his Child be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it attains the age of diſcretion: And the care of a tender Phyſitian to his ſick Patient, whoſe ſoul ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathiſes with the ſickneſs of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients body: He has always this great truth in his mind, that he ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be more frail than they, were he rais'd to the ſame Eminency: By this noble conſideration, he bears from them what he would not from any elſe; he perſiſts in ſerving them when all others forſake them; he prays for them when all the World doth curſe them, and without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble renders them the Religious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which all Laws give unto them; he bears always in mind the the ſaying of the antient Poet, <note place="margin">Senec. Epig. 41. <hi>de Exilio ſuo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Res est Sacra Miſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was Sun ſet, when <hi>Caeſarion</hi> had ended this Diſcourſe: I cannot deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the impreſſions it made on my
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:109194:93"/>mind, and I did not perfectly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, but by the uſe I ſince made of it. I only remember that going after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to walk in a Garden, that fronted his Houſe, to take the freſh air; I was ſo concern'd, that I could not ſpeak a word all that Evening, nor do any thing but look at him, as if I had never ſeen him before: Any body beſides him would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it with pleaſure, and would have let me gone on in my folly, but he laugh'd at me as ſoon as ever he perceiv'd it: Whether it was by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or by much ſtudy, he was wholly inſenſible of the pleaſure that ſelf-love uſually affords. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd to me afterwards in our famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar meetings and diſcourſes, that this indifferency proceeded from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual experience he had of his own defects, and the impoſſibility he found to prevent them; that they were odious to him, and no leſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in his thoughts, than his good Qualities, although perhaps leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd by the World; that it may be every man might ſay ſo much of
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:109194:93"/>himſelf, would they make a diligent ſcrutiny; but moſt did not trouble themſelves in examining their thoughts as ſtrictly as he did, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he knew not if he deſerv'd be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd or to be pity'd. If it were not to be happy to be in this temper of mind, it was at leaſt to be prudent and diſcreet, and you have as great cauſe to lament ſurviving ſo rare a friend, as I have of retaining in my mind a tender and religious Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his admirable great Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Wiſdom.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Fourth Day.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
